<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Baptism without bason. Or, Plain Scripture-proof against infant-baptism, I. By way of answer to Mr. Baxter's arguments, and to the exercitations of Mr. Sidenham, teacher to a church a[t] Newcastle, concerning infants baptism: for which that their pretended consequences are from concessions not to be granted, and from Scriptures as mistaken, and absolutely wrested, is clearly discovered. With II. Several questions and answers, positively holding out the minde of Christ in baptizing of believers onely; and that the magistrates may be induced more and more to encourage the preaching thereof in publike. III. A declaration written to the election of grace, who for want of information are of contrary judgment. Written by William Kaye, minister of the Gospel at Stokesley.</title>
            <author>Kaye, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E715_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207264</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866326</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866326</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87687)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 110:E715[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Baptism without bason. Or, Plain Scripture-proof against infant-baptism, I. By way of answer to Mr. Baxter's arguments, and to the exercitations of Mr. Sidenham, teacher to a church a[t] Newcastle, concerning infants baptism: for which that their pretended consequences are from concessions not to be granted, and from Scriptures as mistaken, and absolutely wrested, is clearly discovered. With II. Several questions and answers, positively holding out the minde of Christ in baptizing of believers onely; and that the magistrates may be induced more and more to encourage the preaching thereof in publike. III. A declaration written to the election of grace, who for want of information are of contrary judgment. Written by William Kaye, minister of the Gospel at Stokesley.</title>
                  <author>Kaye, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ja. Cottrel, for Rich. Moon, at the seven stars in Paul's Church-yard, neer the great North-door.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou. 14.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sydenham, Cuthbert, 1622-1654. --  Christian, sober and plain exercitation on the two grand practical controversies of these times, infant-baptism and singing of Psalms.</term>
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Plain scripture proof or infants church-membership and baptism.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118597:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BAPTISM Without BASON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> Plain Scripture-proof AGAINST INFANT-BAPTISM,</p>
            <p n="1">I. By way of Anſwer to Mr. <hi>BAXTER</hi>'s Arguments, and to the Exercitations of Mr. <hi>SIDENHAM,</hi> Teacher to a Church a Newcaſtle, concerning Infants Baptiſm: for which that their pretended Conſequences are from Conceſſions not to be granted, and from Scriptures as miſtaken, and abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wreſted, is clearly diſcovered. With</p>
            <p n="2">II. Several Queſtions and Anſwers, poſitively holding out the minde of Chriſt in Baptizing of Believers onely; and that the MAGISTRATES may be induced more and more to encourage the preaching thereof in publike.</p>
            <p n="3">III. A DECLARATION written to the Election of grace, who for want of information are of contrary judgment.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>William Kaye,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at Stokeſley.</p>
            <q>And Jeſus being baptized, and praying. <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 3.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>—And the eunuch ſaid, See, here is water; what doth hinder me to be baptized? And Philip ſaid, If thou believeſt with all thine heart, thou mayeſt. — And they went both down into the water, both Philip and the eunuch; and he bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed him. <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 8 36, 37.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Read, and then judge:</hi> withhold not the truth in unrighteouſneſs. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 1.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Ja. Courel,</hi> for <hi>Rich. Moon,</hi> at the ſeven ſtars in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, neer the great North-door. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118597:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118597:2"/>
            <head>To all the brethren of the MINISTERY within the Election of Grace, which unfeignedly deſire to preach Chriſt, and baptize in his Name, in Truth and Sincerity; <hi>Truth and Peace be multiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's very well known, that though the ſtumbling-block which ſome have caſt in the way of Gods people (occaſioned through the falling away of ſome ſtars from the heaven, or fellowſhip of the Churches, is now ſo gloriouſly removed, that divers Saints are return'd to their firſt love; and thoſe that like Caleb and Joſhua (the faithful Churches, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver backſlided) have kept their garments of Goſpel-profeſſion adorned with ſuch meekneſs, truth, and moderation; ſo that they cannot ſhut out Chriſt, as though no Prophet could come out of Nazareth. And now though they may look home, and ſee ſome of their own plants ſo baptized into one body, 1 Cor. 12.14. and kept in ſuch union with Chriſt the Head, and his Body his Churches, as not to walk a ſtep, without a ſtep of their forerunner going before them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.20. And that their conſequences alſo will not uphold Pedo-baptiſm, though they ſhould be granted them; being like the Old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant on which they are grounded, waxen old, as ready to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb facs="tcp:118597:3"/>
away: Yet for all this, you know, that all (the Election of grace excepted) muſt needs ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the Proverb, Can the leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard change his ſpots? <hi>Jer.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.23. And therefore they are ſo blinde, and cannot ſee; deaf, and cannot hear; and are ſo ſet on the lees of obſtinate Reſolution, that they Hate to be Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, until their fleſhly confidence which they had in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-book (the Treaſure of ſome mens knowledge, and to which they ſtick) be crucified with an Order to the contrary: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is to no more purpoſe to ſpeak to ſuch, then to few a piece of New cloth upon an Old garment.</p>
            <p>It's to you therefore, ye ſucceſſors of the noble Bereans, that will ſearch the Scriptures, and try the ſpirit whether it be of God or no, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 ye that prefer Conſcience before Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and preach unto the people, Come out of Babylon; it's you that God hath ſtirred me up to perſwade; and Oh that you may be perſwaded to lay to heart, and to conſider, That in the buſineſs of Infant-ſprinkling, you do not onely contradict your own pretended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight:<note place="margin">Sprinkling is not Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptizing.</note> for Sprinkling is not ſo much Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, as the Picture is the man it repreſenteth, though we ſhould pretend, as we have been taught, that the childe ſhould by its G—fathers and G—mothers believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian faith. But for you to ſprinkle (as ſome of you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) onely the children of believers, and yet to ſprinkle the children of all your Pariſhioners, &amp;c. doth declare, that you have not either preached the Goſpel within your Pariſhes,<note place="margin">Chriſt truly preached, makes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes to be divided.</note> &amp;c. or that it hath not been powerfully received; for the true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Chriſt will ſeparate your people to be called out of the world, to be gathered into the fellowſhip of the Church of Chriſt. Therefore as there is any love to Chriſts name, let us not, I beſeech you, withhold (though it were the tenure of all our eſtates) the truth in unrighteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. For tell me, I pray, ought we to walk by the Glo-worm-light of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, or ſparkles of our own kindling? <hi>Iſa</hi> 50 11 (though the world be confederate, and comply with you) to uphold that darkneſs, againſt the known light, or command and example of the Word of God to the contrary? Or ſhall we exclude Biſhops Government, and Service-Book, and by conſequences contend for Infant-Baptiſm, the greateſt obſtacle to the reforming, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering,
<pb facs="tcp:118597:3"/>
and planting of Churches within your Pariſhes,<note place="margin">Churches to be gathered within Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes.</note> that can be? for if we would not content our ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rather with he fleece then the flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k; if we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re acquainted with the myſteries of the Kingdom of heaven, we might clearly ſee, That as Biſhops Government was uſeful, to hold on a light of Profeſſion to ſuch as were altogether in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he darkneſs of Romiſh Babylon; and as the Presb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terial Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is uſeful to reform Epiſcopacie,<note place="margin">Epiſcopacy, Presbytery, and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency, compared.</note> in reſpect of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernment, Traditions, and Ceremonies, as Independency reforms Presbytery in the point of gathering of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and all of them (as David <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the Temple) make prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for the moſt glorious Apoſtolical Government: ſo that out of all the materials of Truth therein diſcovered, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he golden Candle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ick of Chriſtian profeſſion may be molde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to vaniſh out the ſmoke out of the Temple. Let us but then aboliſh Infant-Baptiſm out of the Church, and the work of Unity, Truth,<note place="margin">The abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of Infant-ſprinkling, in the union of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> and Peace, will be fully compleated. For let Presbyterians gather what they can, if they gather in Chriſts way, to make none of their Church but ſuch as they baptize, upon the profeſſion of faith, as believers: And if the Independents gather none into their Church, but ſuch as believe, and are then baptized; then they ſhall all be united, and centred upon one &amp; the ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Chriſtianity, in their obſervation of the Goſpel-Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Baptiſm, with baptized Churches (commonly, though unjuſtly) called Anabaptiſts: ſo that as Chriſt in his wiſdom fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees but one way, to baptize all nations; ſo this is the only way, to make all Churches out of all nations, to be one in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of faith and obedience. It's no marvel then, if Antichriſt ſtand ſo violently for Pedo-baptiſm; for as all darkneſs came in with it, ſo all light ſhall ſhine, as this darkneſs ſhall vaniſh away, in the adminiſtration of bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing and governing of the Church of believers. And therefore though when darkneſs began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear after the times of the Apoſtles, the braſs and copper of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm being double gilt over with gliſtering pretences, paſſed, like Biſhops government, and other traditions, for currant Coyn; yet this being the time when every plant which our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father hath not planted ſhall be rooted up, whereby the Saints may be reſtored to the primitive profeſſion of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the time of the Apoſtles; Therefore the double-gilded conſequences which are or ſhall be produced, to make an Infant
<pb facs="tcp:118597:4"/>
a baptized diſciple, can expect no better entertainment then Toittis the gray fryer found in Scotland,<note place="margin">Book of Martyrs, p. <hi>1451.</hi> Hen. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> who endeavoured by conſequences to prove that the Pater-noſter might be ſaid to the Saints: which though he did gloſs over, pretending, in that we called aged men father, and that the Saints are in heaven, that therefore we may ſay, Our Father which art in heaven: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their names are holy, we might ſay, Hallowed be their names, &amp;c. But for all his wit, the time of light being come, the Popiſh Church was upon this abſolutely divided, and the Fryer was much derided for his pains. The Lord make us ſeers and followers of his Truth; which, as ſoon as the Lord was pleaſed fully to reveal unto me, I was conſtrained to bear witneſs of it, as I was formerly acted to bear witneſs to the Truth in the time of Innovations, when too many were ſerving at the Altar; by which ſaid power, I was ſtirred up to declare at the firſt, I do not ſay, the firſt that declared, for Reformation: And now I am alſo conſtrained to uſe this plainneſs of ſpeaking (think of me as you pleaſe) wherein I beſeech you to conſider,<note place="margin">See a Book intituled, <hi>the church Regiſter.</hi>
               </note> that Mr. Spering and Mr. Barrow, &amp;c. could not enjoy this liberty to gather Churches, as we may do. This is our day, ſhall we not ſee it? or ſhall we be dead-hearted, ſullen, or not willing to go about our Fathers buſineſs, except we were countenanced or backed out with common approbation? by which we may be thought rather to be driven to our work, then to be that people that ſhall be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in the day of his power, to worſhip the Lord in the beauty of holineſs,<note place="margin">Seed of Martyrs.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.4. Alas, conſider, may not our hearts bleed to ſee, that that ſeed which our Martyrs did ſow with their blood, which did but then peep out with the head, is now white already unto harveſt, and much of it almoſt loſt for gathering into Church-fellowſhip? We muſt not now think to feed all the flock with the pap-milk of ordinary principles; nor will Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Conſequences, which ſhall contradict the command and example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as a ſtrange voice, be poſſibly heard any longer. As we are therefore heirs apparent to all the light which hath ſhined, and have been ſpectators in the time of judgement, of the Lords overturning both of Church and State, becauſe his fore-propheſied time is now fulfilled,<note place="margin">New hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, New Earth.</note> to have a New heaven, or a reformed Church, according to the very example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and a New Earth, or a people, through
<pb facs="tcp:118597:4"/>
oppoſing the old earth, or world, are reformed from Popery,<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Brightm.</hi> Expoſit. on <hi>21</hi> chap. of <hi>Revel.</hi> in part diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering it.</note> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting civil righteouſneſs; which I am able (though I have not here time) to make fully appear, without Allegorizing of the Scripture. Let then all that are Saints, in that the Lord is riſen ſtart fair, and ſee who can firſt run to the Sepulchre; let us ſee who will approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves<note n="*" place="margin">Aurum igne proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, is eſt, cujus fides, rebus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſis splendet.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, tryed gold in the fire, that patronize not a partial, but a perfected inward and outward Reformation; that as wax and ſeal, ſo our faith &amp; obedience may be found indeed agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the doctrine and example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. The Lord raviſh your hearts with the love of this Truth, and remove all preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, until you have read, and ſo may judge, whether I have fully and truely, as far as I have undertaken, anſwered theſe two men of parts, whoſe faces I never ſaw, and againſt whom (I bleſs God) I have not the leaſt prejudice or acrimony nor do deſire to put their light under a buſhel, as far as it appeareth to be light unto me: but onely, as I have been much provoked, deſired, and partly chalenged, I have uſed that liberty which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hath done with Mr. <hi>T.</hi> &amp;c. And therefore I deſire you my dear friends, to commune with your own hearts, and ſee, upon examination on both ſides, what ground you have for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm: And, until the Lord in mercy open your eyes, deſpiſe not the counſel of Doctor <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> to let this alone: for if this be of God. But I have my check; for there is not an <hi>If</hi> in this buſineſs, Chriſt-like to go about our Fathers buſineſs,<note place="margin">No diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Saints, but in Infant-ſprinkling.</note> in ſubmitting to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Ordinance of Baptiſm: for, I hope, as ſoon as Truth ſhall be heard to ſpeak, prejudice being removed, and the moderation of ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Churches, and their full compliance with all the Saints, except in the unwarranted tradition of ſprinkling, being made to appear, the Election of grace (and further we cannot expect) will receive ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to ſubmit to this ſo much deſpiſed Ordinance of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore,<note place="margin">Jeſus Chriſt could not in wiſdome have exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by name, more then in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding to baptize be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers onely.</note> concerning this great matter in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which fills the ears of the whole Country with the report, and is ſo much ſcandalized, belyed, and oppoſed, by the profane and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, this I have to hint unto you, That if Jeſus Chriſt himſelf ſhould come again, and were to reveal himſelf concerning the baptizing of believers onely, he could not in wiſdom exclude children by nome, they being already excluded by Chriſt, in commanding to baptize a taught diſciple: for without mentioning of the female, in comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the male to be circumciſed, the female was expreſly prohibited. For it is, I ſay, againſt the wiſdom of Chriſt, to command to baptize
<pb facs="tcp:118597:5"/>
thoſe that are caught, and thereby are diſcipled, and then to ſay. But baptize not an Infant; ſeeing in wiſdom all men know, that a childe cannot be taught or profeſs the faith of the Goſpel. And beſides, God hath made man judge of Baptiſm, not to proceed as he pleaſeth, but according to the expreſs Rule and Commiſſion which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him. And therefore it is not in man, in favour to the world, and in oppoſition to the Saints of the moſt High, to raiſe Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Allegations, and Reaſonings, to interpret and wreſt the expreſs commiſſion and command of Chriſt to the contrary: but Man if he will be faithful to his Commiſſion, without gainſaying, he muſt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptize none but thoſe that are taught. And therefore it being found, that a childe cannot be taught unleſs man will preſumptuouſly (after due information) break the commandment, he cannot meddle with children, until they be called to the profeſſion of the faith of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. And yet though the ſun of Truth ſhine never ſo clearly, though there be no Truth more fully diſcovered, by expreſs command, and many thouſand examples of baptized diſciples;<note place="margin">None but a Saint will receive any truth, but as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by man, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by cuſtom.</note> yet in regard none but the election of Grace can faithfully receive any Truth, but as it is commanded by Authority, or received by Cuſtom or common Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, in regard the Election of Grace themſelves are like a ſeeing man in a dark dungeon which cannot ſee, till the light of ſeeing be revealed unto them, in taking off their objection or ſcruples to the contrary; I humbly therefore refer you to the enſuing Treatiſe, to judge as the Lord ſhall teach you. And as for the Shining Stars, men of parts &amp;c. that ſhall abet againſt the light of Chriſt, to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the tradition of Antichriſt the Tayl of the Beaſt (which they will not have diſcovered) ſhall draw them,<note place="margin">The tayl of the beast ſtrikes down the ſtars.</note> and caſt them to the earth: for the ſeventh Vial being in part poured out <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1. the ſmoak muſt vaniſh out of the Temple, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. <hi>ult.</hi> Kick not then againſt this prick leſt ye fight againſt God in his diſcoveries; but let us contend for the faith, and ſubmit to the Old truth this ſtep of Chriſt and Chriſtian profeſſion, that it may not ſeem ſtrange in our days, which Chriſt in imitation of himſelf hath ſaid to all ſucceeding ages,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. 3.</hi> expounded, with appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to all Chriſtians.</note> 
               <hi>Thus</hi> that is, according to the example that I your Lord and Maſter was baptized; <hi>it becometh us;</hi> that is, as it was mine, ſo it is all Chriſtians duty to be baptized to fulfil all righteouſneſs. That grace therefore, that calleth out of Babylon, that takes away the envy of Judah and Jeruſalem by which the Saints are baptized into one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be with your ſpirits now and evermore. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Written by your fellow labourer in the Goſpel,</hi> Will. Kaye.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:118597:5"/>
            <head>A Word, by the way, to the preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous Scandalizers and Perſecutors of the gathered Churches, or of all that are called out of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 29.27.</note> Proverb be verified, <hi>The upright in the way is an abomination to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> for which cauſe, they hate, ſcorn, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute all that profeſs Holineſs; and though thoſe<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 9.2, 3, 4, 5.</note> perſecuting ſpirits are as nigh unto ſalvation, as ſome, that are civilly righteous; Yet at <hi>This time</hi> God hath only ſtirred me up, to hint thus much unto you, as the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument</hi> of your Remembrance; That if a viſible Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall not follow the gentle Correction wherewith <hi>England</hi> hath been lately ſummoned, ſo that all viſible evils,<note n="*" place="margin">Levit. 26.23, 24. Iſa. 1.26.</note> droſs and tin, ſhall not be removed, to the puniſhment of thoſe that do evil, and for the praiſe of thoſe that do well; God ſhall ſo renew his <hi>Controverſie</hi> against <hi>You,</hi> for your prophaneſs, ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Zing, and plowing furrows upon the backs of the Saints, that you ſhall once more experience, that the ſame God which puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Prelatical forefathers, that perſecuted the most emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Chriſtians, and hated to be reformed; who led the blinde into the ditch, whereby they, with thouſand of families (their confederates) ſmarted for it,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.34, 35.</note> Shall alſo cauſe a little <hi>Stone</hi> to he cut out without hands, which ſhall ſmite the Image upon
<pb facs="tcp:118597:6"/>
his feet, even your great <hi>Diana,</hi> which ſhall be broken all to pieces, and the little ſtone ſhall become a great mountain. If I ſhould not have told you this, I ſhould have been guilty of the blood of ſome of you:<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.17, 18, 19. Ezek. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Whether you will hear, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will forbear, yet ſhall you know, that there hath been a Prophet amongſt you.</hi> And to as many of you as are of the Election of Grace,<note place="margin">Rev. 18.4.</note> God will call, <hi>Come out of her, my people, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</hi> Until this work of ſaving grace be manifested in you,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.28.</note> you are the objects of the Saints pity, and<note n="*" place="margin">Tim. 2.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>evidences</hi> of their ſalvation; and ſuch inſtruments as Satan hath<note n="*" place="margin">Tim. 2.26, 27.</note> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivated, by which you are acted to oppoſe no profeſsion but that which upholdeth the power of Godlineſs, and is the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal of Antichrist. In meekneſs alſo I deſire to inſtruct you, that you may not kick againſt this prick of Goſpel-information, but be <hi>forewarned to flee from the wrath to come;</hi> which, <hi>Chorazin</hi>-like, in ſlighting the means of Goſpel-information, hath been, and may be occaſioned.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118597:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An ANSWER TO Mr.</hi> BAXTER<hi>'s ARGUMENTS in his Book intituled</hi> Plain Scripture-proof for Infants Chruch-memberſhip and Baptiſm.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the orderly proceeding in the diſcovery there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew,
<list>
                  <item>1. That Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> title to his book is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent.</item>
                  <item>2. His expoſition of Chriſts commiſſion, is er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous.</item>
                  <item>3. His Arguments, whereby he would prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm, are groundleſs.</item>
                  <item>4. And that he hath contradicted himſelf, in ſpeaking evil of the Ordinance of Baptiſm.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Title of his book, <hi>Plain Scripture-proof for Infant-baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. is impertinent, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> cannot but very well (I ſuppoſe) know, that Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> Art. 27. confeſſeth that the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth not pretend any plain or expreſs Scripture-proof for Infant-baptiſm; and that he himſelf hath produced nothing but conſequences, which he hath hammered out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Anvil of Logical Arguments; and that he hath left it ſo myſterious
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118597:7"/>
and difficult, that it is not made ſo plain, that he that runs may read; or that he can tell us, in all the Scripture, in what chapter and verſe we may finde any thing, plainly or expreſly ſpoken for Infant-baptiſm: though on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, we have plain Scripture-proof, or the command and example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, for the baptiſm of believers onely. Neither hath Mr. <hi>B.</hi> for all his diſtinctions, diſpelled the darkneſs, or opened the difficulty, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning infants ſprinkling, which hath brought in all the ſmoke into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And therefore I cannot imagine why Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſhould three hundred four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſix times print his Title, <hi>Plain Scripture-proof,</hi> &amp;c. except he had ſome deſigne to ſatisfie the gazing multitude, to ſacrifice to his net, as the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were moved, upon the inſcription upon the Altar, to proſtrate themſelves to ſuperſtition: And therefore this title, <hi>Plain Scripture-proof,</hi> &amp;c. proves like blue and yellow flowers, making a greater flouriſh, then they are any way advantageous to the reaper. For the true diſcovery thereof, let us ſee what Divinity may be found in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s expoſition of Chriſts commiſſion for Baptiſm.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>B.</hi> chap. 1. pag. 1.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Matth. 28.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Go ye therefore, and diſciple unto me all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That, as a Scholar, he hath ingenuouſly acknowledged the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>Go ye therefore and diſciple unto me,</hi> that is, Go and teach, I do agree with him; and ſo I ſhall, if with the like ingenuity he appear in the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the words, thus rightly tranſlated unto us.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>B.</hi> p. 4.</bibl> 
               <hi>Before I come to argue, I will tell you what is meant by a diſciple. A diſciple may be taken in the larger ſence, as thoſe that are actually believers; and then to the making of a diſciple, ſome things may concur</hi> effective, <hi>and ſome things</hi> condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionaliter.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If Mr. <hi>B.</hi> had gone the plain way to worke, as his title ſo often proclaimeth, then he would have lightned one candle by another, the firſt being lightned from the fire of the Altar; I mean, he would have explained the Scripture, or commiſſion of Baptiſm, by ſome other Scripture: but fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing herein, he hath ſupplyed the want with Logical diſtinctions, a ſtrange voice which the ſheep cannot hear; and therefore, as not acquainted with <hi>conditionaliter,</hi> and <hi>effective,</hi> they cannot give the right hand of fellowſhip to Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s (as being none of Chriſts) diſciple: and therefore while I had thought to have returned an anſwer to thoſe diſtinctions, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled himſelf, in telling us what diſciple he will pitch upon in his next cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, there you may expect a further diſcovery.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>M. <hi>B.</hi> chap. 3. p. 3.</bibl> 
               <hi>By Diſciple, I mean as in the text, thoſe that are</hi> de jure, <hi>or incompleatly Diſciples.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If this be the Diſciple you pitch upon, out of the great choice that you afforded us, Its ſtrange that Chriſt that is moſt glorious in all his works, and in whom the Saints are compleat, ſhould command to baptize an incompleat Diſciple; truly, M. <hi>B.</hi> it were well you had found ſome other
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118597:7"/>
maſter for him, and not Chriſt; As if Chriſt ſhould ſay, Go and make incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Diſciples, which indeed is no leſs then an implicite contradiction, all being compleat in Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10. And I wonder M. <hi>B.</hi> ſhould think a Child an incompleat Diſciple, if he will walk by his own pretended light, in that p. 132. he ſaith, that indirectly, and remotely, the diſcipling of the parent is the diſcipling of the ſeed, and yet the ſeed for all this, though upon his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it be twice diſcipled, yet it is ſtill incompleat, and will be ſo for all M. <hi>B.</hi> can do, though he had his deſire that Children ſhould be cofirmed, that is (to ſpeak plain Engliſh) Biſhopped, <hi>p.</hi> 120. And therefore M. <hi>B</hi>'s diſtinction may ſuit with the Poets fiction, which by caſting of ſtones cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Diſciples, which at firſt were in compleat or <hi>rude,</hi> but afterwards, were more compleated: and therefore it would too much ſavour of partiality, to admit of his Logical diſtinctions, ſeeing in ſtead of expounding, we find the text by M. <hi>B.</hi> ſo confounded, and overvailed with blind and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent diſtinctions; for indeed to tell you the naked truth, baptiſme doth not make a Diſciple, or a believer, though believing Diſciples ſo called by grace, ought to be baptized, that is buried, or covered over, or humbled to God in water, in the name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt: ſo that to be a Diſciple, and baptized, are two diſtinct things, though both are united, or married together in the ſame Goſpel-Ordinance; and therefore M. <hi>B.</hi> ought not to imagine, as the blind world conceiteth, that baptiſme maketh a Diſciple or believer, or as they ſay, a Chriſtian; for to be a believer, and Diſciple, is to be a Chriſtian, who as a Chriſtian, he cannot be ſo adjudged, except he be baptized: And therefore all the courſe that M. <hi>B.</hi> taketh, in ſprinkling or pouring water upon the face of the Child, will not do the feat. Neither can that which M. <hi>B.</hi> ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 14. be approved of, that the matter of a Diſciple in a natural way is nothing, but our being, be granted him, for if by nature, or as we have a natural being, we are Diſciples, then the worke is done to our hand, and Chriſt might have ſaved his Diſciples a great deal of labour in commanding them, firſt to diſciple, by teaching; and then to baptize: And if by nature, or our being, we have that miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous priviledge, why are we called by nature the Children of diſobedience? ſo that for any thing I can find, as none of M. <hi>B</hi>'s diſtinctions are proved by Scripture, he cannot prove that his incompleat diſciple, either in matter, or forme, is the taught Diſciple, that is commanded by Chriſt to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. And therefore I would not have troubled my ſelf any further, but that I find M. <hi>B.</hi> ſo averſe againſt the way of diſcipling according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs command of Chriſt in his text, which he pretendeth to explain unto us, as like the envious man, he denies his own diſcipling, ſaying, <hi>He was diſcipled by education,</hi> p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 133. whereby he puts out both of his own eyes, whereby we might loſe one of our eyes, or he might have a ſandy founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to raiſe an argument againſt diſcipling by teaching: therefore I have this further to tell him, If education made him a Diſciple, then baptiſme did not: and queſtionleſs, if he were well educated, he heard the word, and was <hi>Timothy</hi> like taught the Scriptures <hi>of a Child,</hi> which through the Spririt of grace are able to make us wiſe unto ſalvation: and though a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118597:8"/>
work of grace cannot be diſcovered, yet all education, and knowledge, and waiting, are little enough; or it is but the means that God hath appointed for diſcipling, and yet with M. <hi>B</hi>'s leave, whatſoever he thinks, yet we judge in the rule of truth, that to attain to common knowledge of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion of Chriſt, doth not make a Diſciple, except the day-ſtar hath ſo riſen in his heart, and his judgement be ſo brought unto victory, that he, as is propheſied, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.4. be willing as well as able, in the day of power to ſubmit, as called, or deſire as the Eunuch did in his own perſon to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized: till this work be wrought, we judge one is not (as before baptiſm they ought to be) fully diſcipled: for ſuch a diſcipling as M. <hi>B.</hi> ſpeaketh of, unto which he had attained by education, ſuits with or may ſhake hands with his incompleat Diſciple; And therefore if the Diſciples of <hi>John,</hi> being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the holy Ghoſt, were diſcipled again, and rebaptized, for any thing I can ſee, the work through diſaffection is not ſo compleat, but that <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila</hi> may ſchoole great <hi>Apollo,</hi> and moſt may learn to be Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; ſeeing the incompleat Diſciple, which M. <hi>B.</hi> ſpeaketh of in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, or rather prevarication of the commiſſion of Chriſt, cannot be approved of. <hi>And here</hi> M. <hi>B.</hi> giving over his text, I mean, ſpeaking no more of it then of the firſt words, <hi>Go and diſciple,</hi> he not as I expected proceeding to baptize them, therefore in regard our difference lieth very much concerning the right uſe of the element of water, which by ſprinkling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is not obſerved; that I may therefore ſhew the mind of Chriſt, it being my deſire to give ſatisfaction to my Neighbours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where M. <hi>B.</hi> left off, I ſhall therefore proceed to interpret the Text, <hi>[And baptizing them]</hi> that is, firſt diſciple by teaching, and baptize them, that is, do not pour or ſprinkle a little water in the face of the Child, or partially dip in the head with the heels upwards, for this is not to baptize, nor is the Child the Diſciple that is to be baptized, but the Text tells you whom you muſt baptize; that is, baptize thoſe that are by teaching firſt diſcipled, ſo that their bodies may be buried, or covered over, and humbled upon the acknowledgement of faith and obedience, or upon the pronouncing, I baptize thee in the name of the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the loweſt element of water proſtrated, <hi>Abraham</hi>-like, before the preſence of his Infinite grace and glory. Thus Chriſt himſelf being baptized, and praying, was proſtrated with loweſt ſubjection: and therefore its no marvell M. <hi>B.</hi> was ſilent in ſpeaking of baptiſme, for indeed this contradicting practice in ſprinkling or pouring water upon the face of the Child, would not give liberty to make a handſome interpretation, with application to a Child, concerning bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, or the right uſe of water in baptiſme. To leave then the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of which M. <hi>B.</hi> was ſilent, let us return to ſee his Arguments, which from his unwarranted diſtinctions he indeavours to make his incompleat Diſciple to be baptized.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>B.</hi> chap. 3. p. 15.</bibl> I come now to my firſt Argument, which from my Text is this:
<list>
                  <item>All that are Chriſts diſciples, ordinarily ought to be baptized.</item>
                  <item>But ſome Infants are Chriſts diſciples:</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118597:8"/>Therefore ſome Infants ordinarily ought to be baptized.</item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If Mr. <hi>B.</hi> had kept to his text, he would not have made this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the minor whereof I deny, that Infants are Chriſts diſciples, until, as the text ſayth, they be by teaching made diſciples. And yet Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſo laboureth to make children diſciples, that when the text faileth, he is reſolved it ſeems, by Logical Fallacies, and wreſted Scriptures, to try what can be done; and therefore thus further argueth:
<q>
                  <list>
                     <item>Thoſe on whoſe necks the falſe teachers would have layd this yoke, were diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</item>
                     <item>But ſome of thoſe were Infants on whoſe necks they would have layd this yoke:</item>
                     <item>Therefore ſome Infants are diſciples.</item>
                  </list>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the fallacie in the minor Propoſition may appear, the light that ſhineth <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1. compared with verſe 10. will fully diſcover, that falſe teachers did endeavour to pervert the brethren to be circumciſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10. which ſaid brethren were called diſciples, not by Circumciſion: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that falſe teachers would have had the diſciples, which from Baptiſm were called diſciples, to have been circumciſed, this proves nothing to make children diſciples. If therefore they that pin their faith on Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s ſleeve, will not wilfully cloſe their eyes, they may ſee, that Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in ſtead of producing Scripture to prove a childe a diſciple, it proves to be the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren which had been baptized, which were called diſciples, whom falſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren would have ſeduced to be circumciſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.1, 10. upon which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, or the tampering of the falſe teachers, with the brethren which were diſciples, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> catcheth hold of a ſhadow, or wreſted conſequence, to make a child a diſciple. As if a Preacher were ſeduced, as ſome diſciples were, to be circumciſed; therefore all that are circumciſed muſt be Preachers, or diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. And that the fallacy may now clearly be diſcovered, take this Argument:
<list>
                  <item>Thoſe that the brethren would have converted, are Jewiſh Rabbies, and Popiſh Prieſts.</item>
                  <item>But the Brethren would have Children converted:</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſome children are Jewiſh Rabbies and Popiſh Prieſts.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, my dear friends that know not Logick, and yet have boaſted of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Arguments, you may ſee, if you pleaſe, that as there is a fallacie <hi>a dictu ſimpliciter, ad dictum ſecundum quid,</hi> in this Argument, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by children ſeem to be proved Rabbies, and Popiſh Prieſts: ſo the like fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie is in Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s Argument, whereby he would, from falſe teachers attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting to circumciſe Chriſtians, which are called diſciples, conclude from thence that children may be called diſciples. And now, behold the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures fulfilled; <hi>He taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſs,</hi> Job 5.13. in that thoſe that are of contrary judgement, would not, till of late, grant that none but a diſciple ſhould be baptized: and now not being able to prove their children diſciples, nay, not ſo much as an incompleat diſciple, muſt therefore, if they will make conſcience to ſubmit to the command of Chriſt, let their children &amp; themſelves ſtay until they bed iſcipled, that ſo they may be baptized; and ſo the controverſie may be ended, and, according to the intention of Chriſt, all Chriſtians may be united, in the Goſpel-profeſſion of the Ordinance of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118597:9"/>And yet Mr. <hi>B.</hi> to back out or ſtrengthen his Argument, produceth ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reaſons, to prove a childe a diſciple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> B. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <q>
                  <hi>Becauſe children are partakers of Gods protection.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That God, as God of providence, to children and all creatures, making his ſun to ſhine on the evil and on the good, doth not make children and all creatures diſciples, whoſe duties is to learn to know and follow the ſaid God which is ſo good and merciful, in learning to know God, and following of God, and in not being protected by God, are called diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.24.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſayth, <q>
                  <hi>Children are devoted to learning, therefore they may be diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though children be devoted to learning, and may learn, yet I hope Mr. <hi>B.</hi> would not have them to commence before their time; nor upon this account, while they are a learning, and the ſeeds of a diſciple ſown in them, reap the corn, before it be grown up, and white unto the harveſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>B.</hi> p. 18.</bibl> 
               <hi>If Infants be not Diſciples, it is becauſe they are not capable, or becauſe God will not ſhew them mercy: but neither of theſe can be the cauſe.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To aske the reaſon of God thus in point of ſalvation, <hi>why haſt haſt thou made me ſo?</hi> is liable to that reproof, which upon the like account <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>What art thou O man, that that thou replieſt againſt God?</hi> hath not Chriſt already told Mr. <hi>B. That he that will be his Diſciple, muſt deny himſelf, take up his Croſs and follow him?</hi> Mat. 16.14. muſt not every thing be as God hath determined by his will, and not as the thing is capable? for ſo a poor man is capable to be rich, and a ſick man to be healthfull, and yet while poor and ſick, they are not ſaid to be rich and healthfull: but to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Mr. <hi>B. datur tertium,</hi> a Child cannot be a Diſciple, becauſe it is an implicite contradiction, as to ſay a wiſe fool, for a Diſciple is not a Child, nor a Child a Diſciple: and beſides, that Diſciple which is to be baptized, muſt not be hid or ſecret, but man muſt ſo ſee and judge of him, as from full ſatisfaction proceed to baptize him, when by teaching the party is diſcipled; and therefore God in his wiſedome, that giveth every thing its name, doth not approve of calling a Child a Diſciple, neither can bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme make a Child or any man a Diſciple: how would Mr. <hi>B.</hi> then make a Child a Diſciple, but becauſe by grace as any is taught to profeſs to follow Chriſt, and is ſo diſcipled as a Diſciple, and as a believer, we do baptize them? Thus having anſwered Mr. <hi>B.</hi> firſt Argument, and reaſons whereby he would have proved a Child a Diſciple, his enterprize failing to prove a Child a Diſciple, to make work for Poedo-baptiſme, he produceth this his ſecond Argument.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>B.</hi> 2 Argu. chap. 4. p. 23.</bibl> 
               <hi>My ſecond Argument, and therefore the cheife I make uſe of, is this.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>All that ought to be admitted viſible Church-members, ordinarily ought to be baptized.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But ſome Infants ought to be admitted viſible Church-members:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore ſome Infants ordinarily ought to be baptized.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118597:9"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Of this <hi>ſecond Argument, Mr.</hi> B. giveth this ſuperlative <hi>encomium,</hi> that this is his chief: but believe me, if he could have made his firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment good, whereby a Child might have been diſcipled, he then had had commiſſion for what he had ſaid; and therefore he failing to make his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compleat diſciple to be baptized, he would now ſee what he can do to make a conſequence from his firſt Argument, whereof this ſecond is but a ſhadow: for if Children be not Diſciples, they can be no members of the Church viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but they are not Diſciples; for indeed, to be a diſciple, a member of a viſible Church, differeth no more, then that a man that intendeth to liſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a Souldier, and is approved of, onely wanteth an opportunity to have his admiſſion or approbation: ſo a Diſciple, as ſoon as he declares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and is willing to yeild himſelf up to ſerve God with his Saints, is made a viſible Church-member: but that this work of wonder did ever appear in Infants, that they were ever heard thus to declare their good affection to the government of Chriſts church, I never yet heard; and as ſoon as I hear them, I will ſubmit to Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s. Arguments, and ſay, that thoſe Children thus decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelves for Chriſt and his Church, muſt needs be admitted viſible Church-members: but till this appear viſibly, I deſire Mr. <hi>B.</hi> would content to forbear to intrude them, ſince Chriſts commiſſion will not give leave for ſuch to be baptized, in his name, that know not Chriſt, or yet have not named him; and yet Mr. <hi>B.</hi> to prove his ſecond Argument, forgetting his promiſe, that he would not meddle with other mens Arguments, hath ſcraped up all the thred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd impertinent conſequences, that any before had pretended, to have blocked up the mouth of the Cannon, or to make the worke more tedious to gain-ſay or oppoſe him: while therefore I was intending to have lighted a Candle to have diſcovered, or rather diſpelled this great cloud of darkneſs, Providence ſo ordered it, that a book, intituled <hi>A Chriſtian, ſober, and plaine Exercitation on two grand practical controverſies of this time, Baptiſme and ſinging of Pſalmes, writen by</hi> C. Sidenham <hi>teacher to a Church of Chriſt in</hi> New-caſtle, being brought unto me, and I finding upon peruſal thereof, that it treated as ſufficiently of all Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> conſequences, and with no leſs advantage to his cauſe; and in that Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> with his party, hath as powerfull an influence to ſtop an ear; Therefore I thought that I might bear better teſtimony to the truth, to, anſwer Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Sidenhams</hi> booke: in which way I take no more liberty then he hath done with the right worthy and Apoſtolical Mr. <hi>Tombes.</hi> And yet before I proceed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my promiſe, I deſire to hint ſomething to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> upon the fourth particular, which I firſt mentioned.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That Mr. <hi>B.</hi> hath contradicted himſelf in ſpeaking evill of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſme, as by his two Arguments will appear, is to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> chap. 12. p. 134. his firſt Argument.</bibl>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That which is a plain breach of the ſixth commandment, is no Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, but a moſt hainous ſin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the ordinary practice of dipping the head in cold water, is a breach of the ſixth commandment.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>it is a moſt hainous ſin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118597:10"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is impoſſible that an effectually called Child of God, can raiſe this Argument, without check of conſcience or contradiction, he approving of the way of baptiſme in Braſill, and yet in his Argument contradicts the ſame practiſe of Chriſt, upon the pretence of the cold climate, and cuſtome of the Country. Alas, Alas, this needs no anſwer: for hereby the Scripture is experienced, <hi>their o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ongues ſhall make them fall,</hi> or at leaſt Mr. <hi>B.</hi> I hope is aſhamed, or may be aſhamed of this cavilling ſcandalous Argument, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Chriſtians ſubmiſſion to the Ordinance of Chriſt a hainous ſin, and in telling us it is good for nothing but to diſpatch men out of the world, and to ripen Church-yards, theſe be his words. What if he had lived in the time of circumciſion? he that can diſpence to prevaricate Chriſts command in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, by pouring a little water, or ſprinkling a Childs face with two or three drops of water, certainly, if acted with the ſame Spirit, he would have thought the ripple of a pin, or a drop or two of blood to be ſpilt, to have been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to have anſwered the command in circumciſion.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> 2 Argument.
<q>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If it be a breach of the ſeventh commandment, Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery, ordinarily to baptize naked, then it is an intolerable wickedneſs, and not Gods command.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>But it is a breach of the ſeventh command to baptize naked:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Therefore it is an intolerable wickedneſs, and not Gods command.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I am aſhamed to name Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> lightneſs in mentioning (upon ſuppoſition onely) the Maids of <hi>Bewdley,</hi> though we have no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for being baptized naked, nor any thing againſt it: and therefore as an indifferent thing, a Saint may as well be baptized naked, as Saints pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied naked; yet it is well known that Garments with decency are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of. And will Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> argue againſt an Ordinance, becauſe ſome probable evill may enſue? why then doth he adminiſter the Lords Supper, ſeeing probably ſo adminiſtred, many eat and drink their own damnation, not diſcerning the Lords Body? or why doth he allow of marriage, meat, drink, and apparell, ſeeing abuſe hath been found in them? why doth he therefore upon uncertain conjectures, ſpeak evill of the way of God, in the adminiſtration of baptiſme? may he not be aſhamed thus to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict himſelf? what is Chriſts command to be obſerved in a hot Country, and not in a cold? when were any killed with any one of the diſeaſes that he hath reckoned? though to ſome thereof baptiſme hath been a preſent remedy.</p>
            <p>In regard therefore Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath ſo preſumptuouſly, ſhameleſly, ſcandalouſly, and malignantly ſpoken evill againſt the expreſs command of Chriſt, and that very way which Chriſt had ſubmitted unto, when he like the Eunuch went down and came out of the water after he was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, I can ſay no more, but without any acrimony declare my Chriſtian judgement as by the fruits doth appear, that ſo many Scriptures are fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> ſelf-expreſſions, that herein he hath like the troubled Sea caſt not onely mire and dirt on the face of the Saints, but hath calumniated the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, ſo that in theſe two Arguments
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118597:10"/>
the ſmoak in the Temple hath blinded his eyes: and as he is looked upon by the common people, and cried up in defending this practice of popery, the taile of the beaſt hath ſtrucken him as a ſtarre to the earth, or brought him to a compliance or friendſhip with the world, where I leave him to God that can raiſe him, not doubting but if he were further diſcipled, then by education, he will ſee that all that he hath ſpoken againſt the Ordinance, and renowned Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> as hay and ſtubble ſhall ſuffer burning. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I leave all men to judge, how unjuſtly he hath alledged a Child to be a Diſciple, and therefore leaving Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> I do friendly betake my ſelf to anſwer Mr. <hi>Sidenham.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <head>
               <hi>An Anſwer to Mr.</hi> Sidenham<hi>'s Book, INTITULED,</hi> A Chriſtian, Sober, and Plain Exercita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on two grand Practical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of theſe Times; <hi>Infant-Baptiſm, &amp; Singing of Pſalms.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 1. page 1.</bibl> 
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I enter into the main Queſtions handled in this Diſcourſe, firſt, let this be conſidered, that there is nothing in all the New Teſtament againſt baptizing of Infants, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from any expreſs word dropping from Chriſt nor his Apoſtles, nor any phraſe, though never ſo much ſtrained, doth forbid ſuch an act.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> If you will underſtand nothing in Scripture to be expreſly againſt any thing, except it do by name ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, then Ships, Bells, and unbelieving Gentiles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not expreſly prohibited to be baptized: for this is repugnant to the wiſdom of God and man, to expreſs the prohibiting of any thing by name, when the ſame thing, as not ſpoken unto in another thing, is excluded: and therefore when Chriſt bade <hi>Thomas</hi> put his finger into his ſide, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> they not being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118597:11"/>
               <hi>Thomas</hi> which was ſpoken unto, without naming of them, were expreſly by Chriſts word prohibited: And ſo the female, though never named, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly prohibited, when the male was commanded to be circumciſed. Upon the ſame account, Infants (though not named) are expreſly prohibited to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, or to partake of the Lords Supper, though thereby the Church is made <hi>one body,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.26. in that none, but thoſe that have faith, and examine themſelves, are commanded to receive the Ordinances, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36, 37. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. And therefore, as by confeſſion of thoſe that are of contrary judgement, there is expreſs Scripture to keep Children from the Lords ſupper; ſo we have expreſs Scripture to keep them from Baptiſm, until they ſhall, according to the command of Chriſt, be diſcipled, by teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſhall profeſs the faith in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> endeavouring, pag. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. ſhewing by divers Reaſons, why Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences are to be approved of; to this I anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do allow of Conſequences, provided they be not (as in caſe of Baptiſm) brought in to contradict an expreſs command or example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles to the contrary. And yet though Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s Conſequences be ſuch as oppoſe the expreſs command of Chriſt, as not to deny his Plea, for information, and tryal of the Truth, I ſhall not deny to anſwer them.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 2. pag. 9.</bibl> 
               <hi>The firſt great thing in this controverſie, is, to conſider the nature of this covenant, which is the firſt foundation of the priviledge of believers, and their ſeed; and as it was firſt made to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his ſeed, both Jews and Gentiles. And if we finde the ſame Covenant reaching Gentile believers and their children, as</hi> Abraham <hi>and his, we cannot be denyed the new external ſigne and ſeal of the ſaid Covenant.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the nature of the Covenant ſhould be the foundation-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of beleivers and their ſeed, though I ſhould, as others have, grant him; yet how juſtly upon triall I conceive it will appear, that the Covenant which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and Mr. <hi>B.</hi> looketh at, if it be truly according to its nature diſcovered, they will come ſhort of their expectations: for it appears unto me, that the Covenant only relates to temporall promiſes, in which it had ſo large extent, that all the Nation claimed it: yea circumciſion was a meanes whereby every one was made of the Nation, or endenized, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. ſo that the Nation claimed it as their diſtinguiſhing fleſhly character, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. being their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayl to an earthly inheritance: for the diſcovery whereof, and that we may ſee the true riſe and motive cauſe of the inſtitution of this covenant whereof cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is a ſigne, which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> I ſuppoſe would have to be the foundation of the priviledge of believers; thus it appeareth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. that God telling <hi>Abraham</hi> upon his complaint of being childleſs, and asking God what he would give him, God ſaid, <hi>he would multiply his ſeed as the Starres of Heaven for number,</hi> ver. 5. which <hi>Abraham</hi> believing, it was imputed unto him for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, ver. 6. upon which ſame day God made a Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> ver. 18. ſo that <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12. God relates again the ſame covenant with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> that his ſeed, &amp; all that ſhould relate to <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſhould poſſeſs the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> &amp; to the great river <hi>Euphrates,</hi> &amp; therefore as a ſigne &amp; token of this temporall Covenant, God ordained circumciſion as his token thereof betwixt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118597:11"/>
God and his people, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. and however Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and Mr. <hi>B.</hi> &amp;c. have wreſted the Scripu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, as I ſhall by and by ſhew, in making this temporall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant a Covenant of grace, and as relating unto the admiſſion into the Church, yet I hope fully and clearly to prove the contrary: for as though the Lord would undeceive and ſatisfie the Jews, why he tooke away the firſt old Covenant, on which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and Mr. <hi>B.</hi> &amp;c. like the Jews do too much dote, he declareth himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7. ſaying, that if the firſt Covenant had been good, that is, if it had related to the good of their ſouls, then there had been found no place for the ſecond, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. So that the covenant which was taken away, was the covenant of temporal promiſes, as the contents to <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. calls it, whereof circumciſion was the ſigne, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. for the cauſe that God alleadgeth, why he tooke away the old Covenant, is fully and plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. by which it doth appear, that that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of which circumciſion was a token, was aboliſhed in all intents and purpoſes: and the new Covenant, not made according to the old Covenant, is onely eſtabliſhed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.9, 10. and therefore the old Covenant which is aboliſhed, upon which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> would build a foundation, is fallen to the ground: and how then ſhall his doctrine for which he hath no foundation, to make the ſeed of believers Church-members by vertue of the Covenant of which circumciſion was a token, be able to ſtand, ſeeing it is ſo abſolutely condemned and taken away. M. <hi>S</hi>'s and M. <hi>B</hi>'s conſequence for circumciſion cannot be admitted of, that Children upon that pretence ſhould have bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, of which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> is much miſtaken, in that he calleth baptiſme the new externall ſigne, and ſeal of the Covenant, he having no Scripture to prove what he ſaith, neither can he prove that baptiſme is a ſeal at all; neither is there any ſuch thing in the covenant, to be ſigned or ſealed, he as conceiteth: Yet,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> p. 10.</bibl> Saith, <hi>Firſt and chiefly we affirm, this</hi> (meaning circumciſion) <hi>was the ſame in ſubſtance with the Covenant adminiſtred under the Goſpel, ſince Chriſts coming in the fleſh and ſpirit. Secondly, It was founded on pure grace.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt then, and chiefly, I anſwer, that here is a confounding of things that differ, circumciſion being called a Covenant, but figuratively, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. It being in its own Nature the token of the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. ſo that Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> ſaying, that circumciſion is the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with the Covenant in the Goſpel, is partly miſtaken, as alſo in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring circumciſion with baptiſme; he being not able to finde any proof in Scripture, that baptiſme is either Covenant, or Seal. Secondly, And that circumciſion is not the ſame in ſubſtance with the Covenant under the Goſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8 expreſly declareth, that when the Covenant whereof cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is a token, and the new Covenant, are compared, that the new Covenant is eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes, <hi>Heb</hi> 8.6. then a temporall inheritance. And yet Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> would have the beſt of promiſes in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, as in the next place doth appear, in that he ſaith, that cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was founded on pure grace, and that it was a pure Covenant of grace, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16, 17, 18, 19, 29.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118597:12"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That it may truly and clearly appear, Firſt, that the Scriptures he produceth, witneſs againſt him; And ſecondly, that he hath not rightly applied them, let us obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That that which he alleadgeth <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. that the promiſes were not made to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeeds, as of many, but as of one, to thy feed, which is Chriſt: though we take this for Chriſt myſticall, as Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> would have it, yet here is nothing relating to circumciſion, in which, if we mind, it is ſaid, the promiſes were made not to the ſeeds, which was of <hi>Hagar</hi> and ſtrangers, as well as of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> which promiſe had reſpect to circumciſion: therefore thoſe promiſes being excluded, which had reſpect to the ſeeds of many, there is nothing of circumciſion ſpoken in the 16. <hi>ver.</hi> but of the promiſe which relates to <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17, 18. and that <hi>ver.</hi> 17. ſpeaketh nothing of circumciſion: there are three things mentioned in the ſaid verſe, Covenant, Law, and Promiſe, the firſt two whereof, the Covenant, and Law, are onely named, as that they could not, or cannot diſannull the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which is made, as I have proved before, unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 22.16, 17, 18. and unto <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, which are the children of God, by grace and faith, called to walk in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Rom. 4.11, 12. as I ſhall preſently more fully declare: therefore in that God made a gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> did believe in God when he ſhould have ſacrificed his ſonne <hi>Iſaac,</hi> therefore this promiſe hath reſpect to <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.18. for you ſee this is not called a Covenant, but a promiſe, which was made to <hi>Abraham, ver.</hi> 16, 17. and therefore that all that is ſpoken by the Apoſtle, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. as is above mentioned, as the verſes are alledged by Mr. <hi>Sidenham,</hi> Gal. 3.16, 17, 18, 19. doth not hold forth any thing to make Mr. <hi>Sidenhams</hi> pretence, that circumciſion is founded on pure grace, or to be a Covenant of pure grace, is fully diſcovered: And therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in the next place, I may make it appear, that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hath not rightly apprehended theſe Scriptures, in calling circumciſion from thence a Covenant of pure grace; This I ſay, To be founded on pure grace, or that God of his pure grace or good will was pleaſed to look on <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo as to give him a temporal promiſe, or a ſeed according to the fleſh, is not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied; yet this makes not the gift to be pure grace: as if God in his pure grace give the wicked meat, drink and cloathing, doth not prove that their meat, drink, and clothing is pure grace. Therefore however circumciſion, the ſigne of temporal mercies, was given on Gods part of his pure grace, it makes not the Covenant to be pure grace, which, as I ſaid, in the contents of the 8. chap. to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> is called a Covenant of temporall promiſes: for all ſpirituall promiſes which were made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> were not by vertue of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but in that, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. God foreſeeing that he would juſtifie the Heathen through faith, preached the Goſpel unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> ſaying, <hi>In thee ſhall all Nations be bleſſed:</hi> which words are expreſly mentioned, <hi>Gen</hi> 22.18. and cannot be found <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. circumciſion relating to Nations that ſhould come of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, in which temporall promiſe the Gentiles had no Intereſt, but as they ſubmitted to the <hi>Jews;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its clear enough, or the Sun cannot ſhine more clearly, then that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118597:12"/>
the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> being believers, or walking in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gal. 3.7, 9. Rom. 4.12. circumciſion the token of a temporall covenant, did not hold forth this ſpirituall mercy, which God upon <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing of his Sonne, promiſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> even to bleſs all Nations in him, as hath been at large diſcovered. And therefore that which Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> ſaith, that the Apoſtle uſeth the ſame expreſſion in <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. where he ſpeaketh of the new Covenant, which was, as Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> pretendeth, uſed <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed;</hi> In this he may ſee how partially he is blaſted to favour his own imagination. For firſt, God doth not onely ſay, as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>I will be a God unto thee, and thy ſeed after thee,</hi> but in the new Covenant he ſaith not onely, that <hi>He will be a God unto them, and they ſhall be a people unto him:</hi> but to ſhew that this new covenant is upon better promiſes, God ſheweth that he will work a work of grace, even to write his Lawes in their hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this God never promiſed in circumciſion: and that God in circumciſion did onely (it relating to all the world) promiſe no more, then to be a God in providence unto them, or to make good his promiſe or covenant to give them the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land, read <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.44, 45. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 13.22, 23. and there you ſhall fully be informed: and therefore you may ſee, that circumciſion is no covenant of pure grace, or equivalent with that new covenant under the Goſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. which is ſaid to be eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. which could not be, if Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> might have liberty to exalt it above meaſure, and plead a falſe title, or uphold that which by Chriſt and his Church hath been totally taken away, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I muſt tell Mr. <hi>Sidenham,</hi> which it may be may ſeem to him ſtrange, that God having made man judge of baptiſme, whereby man muſt look at what is viſibly revealed, and not contradict his commiſſion upon the uncertain conſequences of ſecret pretences, therefore the old covenant, as altogether made void and impertinent, is not onely waved, but alſo the gracious new covenant which is in force, except it ſhould be revealed or manifeſted, ſo that through diſcipling and profeſſion of faith, we could judge of it, (ſecret things belonging unto God) were no ground or conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of baptiſme, nor to proceed upon the promiſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. untill that time that they ſhould be called.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 3. p. 16.</bibl> 
               <hi>The next thing which must have its place of conſideration, is that queſtion of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham's <hi>ſeed, with whom the promiſe was made: and on this bangs all the main weight on both ſides. And if we make Infant believers to be in Covenant, as</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham<hi>'s ſeed, the controverſie will be at an end. There is a carnal and a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſeed, under the New Testament, as our oppoſites muſt acknowledge.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The firſt great thing (as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> is pleaſed to call it) the nature of the Covenant, his foundation being thrown down, I cannot ſee how the door of hope, in this third chapter, can have a hinge to hang upon: neither can your oppoſites, in your ſenſe, acknowledge your diſtinction, if by <hi>ſpiritual ſeed</hi> you underſtand the children of believers, before they be, by being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and made actual believers, made <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſeed, in walking in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118597:13"/>
ſteps of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Rom. 4.12, 16. Therefore as the promiſe was made to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> both the ſeed and the promiſe muſt be diſtinguiſhed. As <hi>Abraham</hi> had a natural ſeed, it was either that which he had of <hi>Hagar,</hi> called <hi>the ſeed according to the fleſh;</hi> or of <hi>Sarah,</hi> called <hi>the ſeed according to the promiſe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God gave it by promiſe: both which ſeeds ſpoken of, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.23. are both of them to be accounted the ſeed according to the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. and ſo the promiſe made unto them upon this account, was the Covenant of which Circumciſion was a ſigne; that is to ſay, temporal promiſes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. as I have before fully proved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But <hi>Abraham</hi> hath alſo a ſeed of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. that is, all believers, both of the Circumciſion, and of the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12. which as they walk in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham,</hi> are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> he is their father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12, 16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9. compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.23, 30. And therefore if in this ſenſe Mr. <hi>S.</hi> underſtand a <hi>ſpiritual ſeed,</hi> which the Scripture calleth <hi>a ſeed of faith,</hi> Rom. 4.16. I ſhall grant him: but if he imagine that the ſeed of faith came by Circumciſion, or that it is, as he ſaith, Infant-belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, then I deny it: for I do affirm, that the ſeed of faith came by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and oath which God made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> upon the attempting of ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of his ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> whereby <hi>Abraham</hi> to be father to the ſeed of faith, both thoſe that are circumciſed, and of the Gentiles, was then promiſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17, 18. compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13, 14. So that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and I do not ſo much differ about <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſeed in a ſpiritual relation, which properly called, is <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed by faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. as we differ, that he would make a ſpiritual ſeed by Circumciſion, and in Infants, which till they be believers, are not ſo called: ſo that Infant-believers as conſidered to be Infants, were not in covenant, as M.S. pretendeth, further then in that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant whereof circumciſion was a ſigne, whereby onely the Infants of <hi>Jews,</hi> or ſuch as were made <hi>Jews</hi> by circumciſion, had as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall promiſes, made good unto them, of <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that here again Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſtumbles upon circumciſion: neither had I ſaid this, but that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> will not let us be quiet. But, which is worſe, with reflection upon circumciſion, and to get a conſequence to maintain the dotage of popery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby they hold Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren damned if they be not baptized; Mr. <hi>S.</hi> thus far further advanceth his cauſe with hay and ſtubble, ſaying, <hi>p.</hi> 21. there is a ſecret diſtinction and veine of election, carried through the adminiſtration, which takes hold of ſome, and not of others; as if the election or promiſe were made, it ſhould not be effectuall, without that adminiſtration: but bleſſed be God, he hath not produced any Scripture, to ſow this piece of old cloth on the new garment of the Goſpel: of which I thought to have made a farther diſcovery, but that circumciſion being again brought upon the ſtage, I am called to anſwer in that.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> p. 14.</bibl> Saith, <hi>Let us come to circumciſion the ſeal of the covenant.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the vail of fleſh, which through circumciſion hangs over M.<hi>S</hi>'s eyes, may be removed, that he may look above circumciſion, the Scripture may inform him that circumciſion is not a ſeal of the covenant, but it is onely
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118597:13"/>
a Token of the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. and though it is called a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 15.6. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. yet this makes not circumciſion a ſeal of the covenant; and if it were, it could not ſeal more then is in the covenant, that is, temporall mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: and as it was the ſeal of <hi>Abrahams</hi> righteouſneſs, which he had before circumciſion, and not given by circumciſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.10. with whom the covenant was firſt made. To this I anſwer, that circumciſion as a ſeal relating to <hi>Abraham,</hi> holds forth Gods approbation of <hi>Abraham:</hi> as ſigns and miracles did confirm the approbation of the faith of the Apoſtles, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17. and the converſion of the people is the ſeal or approbation of the Miniſtery, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2. that therefore every ones faith muſt be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, God not beginning an adminiſtration, or not making an originall covenant with them, but doing for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake, or chuſing theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to be choſen witneſſes, is neither conſonant to Scripture, or reaſon: ſo that the Scripture in the old Teſtament never ſpeaks more, then that circumciſion is a ſigne of the covenant made in the fleſh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. and as it relates with reſpect of a particular application to <hi>Abraham,</hi> it was the ſeal of his righteouſneſs, which, as I proved before, was not by means of circumciſion: and though we do diſclaim <hi>Abraham</hi> to be our Father by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, in that thereby he was but a Father of ſome Nations, all being <hi>Jews,</hi> or made <hi>Jews</hi> by circumciſion, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.15. yet we do own <hi>Abraham</hi> as to the example of faith, as Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> rightly ſtates it, to be our Father, from the Oath and Promiſe God made to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Gen. 22.16, 17, 18. compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12, 16.</p>
            <p>Now that <hi>Abraham</hi> was a believer before, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. ſo that God did bleſs <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that circumciſion did ſeal his Faith he had though not as the Apoſtle ſaith by circumciſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. I do grant: but that God gave <hi>Abraham</hi> in circumciſion, more then <hi>Abraham</hi> begged of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.3, 48. or that God did give <hi>Abraham</hi> more then an inheritance of which circumciſion was a token, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4, 11. this I defend: and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore circumciſion was not an adminiſtration to make Church-members, I deſire (this being ſo much miſtaken) to produce theſe reaſons to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they did not circumciſe in the Temple, or by a Prieſt, but a woman, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.25. and others did circumciſe, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſtranger by circumciſion, was not ſaid to be of the Church, but as one of the Nation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48, and if any refuſed to be circumciſed, they were not to be excommunicated out of the Church, but to be cut off out of the Nation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14. and that the Church is not the Nation, Reaſon the ſeventh proves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Female was not circumciſed, and yet <hi>Hanna</hi> and other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were of the Church: and if in the Man the Woman might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Church, why might not the Woman in the Man be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and receive the Lords Supper? ſince they would have baptiſm to ſucceed circumciſion,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe God ſaid, that the Covenant of which circumciſion was a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118597:14"/>
ſigne, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. was a covenant in the fleſh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.13. and God did never promiſe more then a temporall inheritance in that covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.3.18. compared with <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.3, 4, 5, 8.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In the caſe of <hi>Dinah</hi> marrying with <hi>Sichem,</hi> all that was deſired of him, was this, that they ſhould be one people, if <hi>Sichem,</hi> &amp;c. would be circumciſed: which was done without any change of religion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.22, 24. and though it might be ſuppoſed (as we do with our children) they would endeavour to learn them, and make them ſubmit to their Religion; yet all this endeavouring, like the paines that we take in the nurture and admonition of our Children, did not admit or make them viſible Church-members, but onely made preparation for their admiſſion: as the next reaſon will fully clear it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Becauſe to the <hi>Jews</hi> God ſaid, <hi>Gather my Saints together unto me, thoſe that have made a covenant with me, by ſacifice.</hi> Pſal. 50.5. and <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9. its propheſied both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that they ſhould <hi>ſerve God with one conſent;</hi> Therefore Children not ſacrificing, whereby there might be a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble appearance of Faith and Repentance, and they not being willing or knowing <hi>to ſerve God with one conſent,</hi> could not be of the viſible gathered Church, or they were not viſible Church-members: for to make a viſible Church member, there muſt be ſomething appearing in the party that is to be admitted, ſo as to give his conſent: but in a Child we have or ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that repreſents the face of a Church-member.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Children by circumciſion were not made Church-members, becauſe after they had been circumciſed, they were preſented unto the Lord in the Temple: and our Saviour did no more for them, when they were brought unto him, then bleſs them, by praying for them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p n="8">8. God was ſaid to have a Church in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.38. and yet for forty yeers together they were not circumciſed: and therefore circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion made not a Church, if baptiſm, as Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> ſaith, doth not make one; for ſo he ſaith, pag. 166. <hi>Baptiſme doth not forme a Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Becauſe the Gentiles had a Church, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath notably proved by <hi>Job,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Abraham</hi> was of the Church before, and yet the Gentiles were never circumciſed, and <hi>Abraham</hi> had not been circumciſed, but that God made circumciſion a ſigne of the covenant, which was to give him a ſeed by <hi>Sarah,</hi> and to make him a Father, and <hi>Sarah</hi> a Mother of divers Nations, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.6, 16. for as all Nations whether <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> are bleſſed in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> this was not by circumciſion, but by oath and promiſe made to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6, 17, 18. as the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.9. compared with <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13, 14. fully declareth: and therefore we do not look at circumciſion, that it did admit unto the Church, or that baptiſm ſhould ſucceed it, circumciſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to temporal promiſes.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Becauſe theſe words in the covenant whereof circumciſion is a ſigne, <hi>I will be thy God, and o thy ſeed after thee,</hi> were onely ſpoken of God, that he might manifeſt himſelf to be a God in providence, to make his temporal promiſe good to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſuch ſtrangers that ſhould ſojourne with him: God excepting againſt none in circumciſion, as he doth in point of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118597:14"/>
ſalvation: and therefore God expreſly declared his meaning, that in reſpect of the covenant whereof circumciſion was a ſigne, he was their God to make good his promiſe to give them the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Levit. 26.44, 45. and in that he condemned and tooke away this circumciſion, making a new covenant, not according to the old covenant, declares that the old cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant had no ſpiritual promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> making circumciſion to bring Children into the Church, is but from their own wreſted conſequences, for there is no ſuch Scripture that ſaith, Circumciſion makes a Child a member of the Church, neither is there any Scripture that can prove circumciſion a covenant of pure grace, or that baptiſm doth ſucceed it, upon which they ground their concluſion or conſequence.</p>
            <p n="12">12. If baptiſm ſhould ſucceed circumciſion, then it could not be ſaid, that baptiſm is the like figure of <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. in which there was no Children, nor did any enter into it, but ſuch as believed the word preached unto them.</p>
            <p n="13">13. They were debtors to the Law, not by covenant or contract (the Law being made four hundred and forty yeers after circumciſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17.) and therefore they were debtors to the Law by conſequence, as a thing that followed, and was after impoſed upon the people; ſo that they were not circumciſed upon that account.</p>
            <p n="14">14. They were twice circumciſed. The firſt time, in token they ſhould inherit the promiſed Land. And the ſecond time, as being come to poſſeſs it, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 5.2. therefore circumciſion did not make them Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>The great thing then which Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> pag. 9. ſpeaketh of in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, the nature of the covenant being fully and plainly diſcovered, its too apparent that he hath been too much diſcipled by the Jewiſh rabbies, in making the Covenant by their traditions and doctrine, greater then ever God intended it, whereby the promiſe and oath God made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> whereby he is the Father of the faithful, hath been over-looked; Therefore Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> failing to make good his hinge and maine weight, in thinking to make all promiſes to <hi>Abraham</hi> as Father to the faithful, to be held out in circumciſion, and that it was a ſeal of the covenant, and baptiſm a ſeal of the new covenant, in all which his errors and miſtakes have been plainly diſcovered: yet I would not have Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> or any of his judgement, to think, that I have denied him that which may be ſome have, or he hath expected to have granted him (as I ſhould readily have done, if it had been Gods truth) in relation to the covenant whereof circumciſion was the ſigne: as though, if Mr. <hi>Sidenhams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> conſequences were granted him, he could thereby prove his infant-baptiſm; for this I ſay, that though he were certain that a Child were in the new covenant of the Goſpel, yet no viſible fruit of holineſs, of profeſſion, of faith, coverſation, and willing deſire of baptiſm being made to appear, ſecret things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto God, and we being commanded as any ſhall be diſcipled to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them; its not in Mr. <hi>Sidenham,</hi> &amp;c. to gainſay Chriſts will and power,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118597:15"/>
to make the admiſſion into the Church, according as he fancieth by any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended pretences, conſequences, or precedents, or to admit a Child, or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant perſon, not being by Chriſt tolerated, ſeeing according to his own pretended light, he did not regulate circumciſion to a former adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither is there any Scripture to prove that baptiſm ſucceedeth cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but both by command and example the Scripture doth prove the contrary; therefore in the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, except Mr. <hi>S.</hi> will flee from Scripture, and juſtifie the falling away from the faith, ſo that in this point of Infant-baptiſm, he ſhould comply with the tradition of Popery, he hath hitherto produced nothing to uphold his controverſie in this great thing, foundation and hinge, which I have anſwered. To proceed then.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> p. 22.</bibl> 
               <hi>Infants, if believers, were never cast out of the viſible Church of Christ, of which they were once in.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> According to that maxime, <hi>Omnis privatio implicat habitum,</hi> you know that every diſpoſſeſſion implieth a poſſeſſion: Infants cannot therefore be caſt out of the Church, before he can prove them admitted: and if Mr. <hi>S.</hi> or any man living can tell us by what viſible adminiſtration, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were admitted viſible Church-members before the time of <hi>Abraham,</hi> or in the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Church, or by what Scripture they are ſaid to be admited members by cirumciſion; I ſhall admire him and them, and acknowledge their diſcovery, deſiring him till then not to conclude, that we do caſt them out, or deny them any thing, that can be conſcientiouſly granted them.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 4. p. 30.</bibl> In that Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> doth make a twofold diſtinction, of being in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, in relation to the election of grace: and ſecondly, to be in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>in facie viſibilis eccleſiae;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I anſwer, firſt, that onely the elect are in covenant of ſaving faith, which is called as he ſaith, by Divines, intentionally in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as God intending onely to ſave them. I agree: onely this may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, 1. That the election of Grace is not by the Covenant whereof Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is a ſigne. 2. That if upon this account, that is, Predeſtination, we ſhould look on children, then children of believers, as well as believers, Papiſts, Turks, and Infidels, may be in the Election, even before they be called; and yet this will give no liberty to children, until their ſecret electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be made viſibly appearing, through a gracious call, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> tells us that there is a being in Covenant <hi>in facie viſibilis Eccleſiae,</hi> in the face of a viſible Church; I confeſs, that a viſible Church ſhould have a race, ſo that they may ſee, hear, and ſpeak with one another, to yeeld up themſelves to ſerve God <hi>with one conſent,</hi> Zeph. 3.9. but how he will make Infants in ſwadling-clouts ſuch viſible members, I know not. For want of ſuch a face of the Church, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> I ſuppoſe excludes Infants from the Lords Supper, though he confeſſeth that thereby the Church is made <hi>one body,</hi> pag. 169. and ſo doth the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17.</p>
            <p>And I do abſolutely deny that ever there was any ſuch Covenant, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of which God ſaid a childe ſhould be counted a member of the viſible
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118597:15"/>
Church. Therefore Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s Scriptures to prove that by Covenant children were brought into the Church, are to be examined.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to that place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> produceth;</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that it onely holds forth the ſeveral priviledges belonging to the Jews, but doth not hint ſo much as one word, that by Circumciſion chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were brought <hi>in facie viſibilis Eccleſiae,</hi> or made members of the viſible Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To that place, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, It is not at all proved that Circumciſion did at all relate to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but that God ſaid that he would make them a people, as he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.6, 16. to make <hi>Abraham</hi> a father of many nations, and ſo <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhould be a mother of many nations, as I have proved before of which Covenant Circumciſion was the ſigne.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To that place, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.2. and <hi>Job.</hi> 1.11. I cannot ſee the leaſt conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of a Covenant.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To the laſt place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Gather my ſaints together,</hi> that is, make a viſible Church; This I acknowledge: but that any children were gathered, the next words tell him who they be that God would have gathered, even <hi>ſuch as have made a covenant with ſacrifice:</hi> not ſuch as are of the covenant whereof circumciſion is but a ſigne, but <hi>ſuch as have made a covenant with me</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>in ſacrifice:</hi> ſo that we finde no ſhadow of proof in the places pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by M.<hi>S.</hi> that children are of the viſible Church. To another relation.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 5. page 35. endeavours to open that place, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>For the promiſe is made unto you and your children,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the pretended opening of which Scripture, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> indeed hath ſo over-veyled the ſame, and ſhut it up in Logical Diſtinctions, Critical Queſtions, and Wreſted Applications, that I may ſay of this Scripture, as the parents ſaid of their ſon, It ſo clearly ſhineth, that it is able to anſwer for it ſelf. Theſe be the words: <hi>Repent and be baptized every one of you, in the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: for the promiſe is made unto you, and to your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> Now the promiſe here, which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> omitted, as the antecedent to be related, was to receive the holy Ghoſt, by ſuch as did repent and were baptized, and who are here ſaid to repent, to be baptized, &amp; to receive the holy Ghoſt: but ſuch of them, and of their children, and them that are afar off, and of their children, with this reſtriction, <hi>even to as many,</hi> and no more, then <hi>the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> So that here is a plain reſtriction, and application to whom this promiſe is made, <hi>even to as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no heart could deſire a more full and plain expreſſion of the minde of God. And therefore Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hath not opened, but ſhut up, or turned the ſtream of thoſe gracious expreſſions of Scripture. And yet upon concluſion, after a great deal of diſcourſe, this chapter conſiſting of almoſt a ſheet of paper, he concludes, that however this Scripture holds forth the promiſe of believers of the Goſpel, both Jews and Gentiles, and their children: which is true, if the laſt words, wherein all the main buſineſs depends, be applied, whereby we may ſee to whom this promiſe is made, even <hi>to as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118597:16"/>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 6. pag. 45. having hitherto endeavoured to plead his own cauſe, by the ſtrongeſt Arguments which by conſequence he could produce, now endeavouring to throw down our foundation in this ſixth chapter, he tells us, that our great plea from <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8, 9. is made vain.</p>
            <p>Theſe be Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That we may ſtill take off the Objections, let us view that place ſo much ſtood on,</hi> Matth. 3.8, 9. When John ſaw many of the Phariſees and Sadduces come to his Baptiſm, he ſayth, O generation of vipers, who hath forewarned you to flee from the wrath to come? Bring forth fruits meet for repentance. And think not to ſay that you have Abraham to your father: for I ſay that God is able of theſe ſtones to raiſe up children unto Abraham. <hi>From this text they gather, The pretence of being Abrahams children could not give them a right to Baptiſm. And if John denyed Abraham's ſeed upon that account, much more would he the adopted children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That this is no ſuch ominous place against Infant-baptiſm, conſider who they were he ſpake unto, the Phariſees and Sadduces, men of age, and degenerate from Abrahams faith, perſons that lived in their own works and righteouſneſs: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he calls them a generation of vipers, which was not as they were Abrahams children, but as they walked not in Abrahams ſteps, and were quite degenerate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer, that the plea is not vain (as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of his chapter pretendeth) that is by us made from <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.8, 9. though to obſcure the light that therein ſhineth, or for Mr. <hi>S.</hi> to light his candle, or gloſs, or interpretation, to darken the ſun-light of expreſs Scripture, is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vain, in that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſay, that <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.8, 9. in the general, is directly againſt Infant-ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, in that none but ſuch as have faith and repentance muſt think to be baptized, is as clear a place as can be deſired or pleaded for.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the pretence or conſequence from Circumciſion, from this of <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>Think not to ſay you have Abraham to your father,</hi> is alſo condemned, it appears that <hi>John</hi> did not judge them to have any benefit or priviledge as being <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed according to the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. whereby <hi>Abraham</hi> was their father by circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.5, 16. And therefore <hi>John</hi> apprehending the Phariſees and Sadduces (as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> &amp;c. do) to ſtile themſelves, through this pretended priviledge from <hi>Abraham,</hi> without looking home for faith and repentance, which every childe of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould have, which calls <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> father by faith, as onely they that believe ought to do, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to undeceive the Phariſees and Sadduces, and to unbottom them, and to throw down their ſandy foundation, that <hi>John</hi> in the ſimplicity of the Goſpel might be downright with them, (though it's true, that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſayth, that he did not call them a generation of vipers, as they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, yet) that they might not through fleſhly confidence make their plea, or reſt upon this account, that they might be baptized, being but <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed according to Law, and not by faith, he tells them (to undeceive them) ſaying, <hi>Think not to ſay that you have Abraham to your father,</hi> as that you ſhould think upon this account, that I ſhould baptize you; therefore <hi>John,</hi> without as much as taking notice (which he would have done, if there had been cauſe) of any
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118597:16"/>
legal priviledge they had by <hi>Abraham</hi> to plead for Baptiſm, onely exhorts them to faith and repentance, by which they are the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12, 16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7. which <hi>John</hi> makes the ground of his admittance unto Baptiſm: unto which Goſpel-ordinance, none but a taught diſciple, by the expreſs and plain words of Chriſt, ought to be admitted. And therefore our plea, that the pretence of being <hi>Abrahams</hi> children by Law, or Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, could not give a right to Baptiſm, as hath been before often proved, is very warrantable: ſo that <hi>John</hi> did not deſire to diſpoſſeſs them, or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion them as the Legal ſeed, or children of <hi>Abraham;</hi> but onely let them know, that they ought not to have ſo much as a thought to get Baptiſm, though they ſhould think to ſay, <hi>We have Abraham to our father:</hi> which in other reſpects, it was both lawful for them to think, profeſs, and affirm, that they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> children according to the Law, but yet not to plead it as a conſequence for Baptiſm, much leſs for their childrens. And, but that I ſtrive not to take advantage upon every occaſion, it's an eaſie thing to prove by the words of Chriſt, in that he did approve of the Phariſees to <hi>ſit in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes chayr,</hi> and of their doctrine; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n that they (as the word <hi>Phariſee</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth) did expound the Scripture; and that the Sadduces were ſtrict living men, that gave much to the poor, though they (admitting of nothing but the letter of the Scripture) denyed the reſurrection: yet, as Authors teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, they were the beſt of the Jewiſh Church, and did uphold circumciſion, though, as many that pretend to the Church, they ſtood for traditions, and had their failings, and, through unbelief in Chriſt, were a generation of vipers: yet that they were quite cut off, and degenerated from <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed by the Law, he cannot prove, as may appear by Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.37, 39. And therefore <hi>John</hi> not approving of them upon this account, as being <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s ſeed according to the Law, makes it clear, that <hi>John</hi> did object both againſt them for their evil lives, and for pretending that they ſhould have Baptiſm, from the pretence that <hi>Abraham</hi> is their father according to the Law, as before ſaid. Therefore we ſtand to our plea, that <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.8, 9. is not onely againſt Infants baptiſm in the general, but alſo againſt the very conſequence which (from Circumciſion, whereby <hi>Abraham</hi> is a father accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law) is pretended, to uphold the ſame. And therefore children were not baptized by <hi>John,</hi> as though, as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſayth, p. 47. they were neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by <hi>John,</hi> as though he could not have got time to attend to baptize them; but, <hi>John</hi> did not baptize them, becauſe they were not <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſeed according to the faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12, 16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7, 9. that is, they were not actually believers, otherwiſe <hi>John</hi> would not have been guilty of ſuch partiality and injuſtice; for <hi>John</hi> refuſed none but ſuch, and all ſuch whatſoever, as in whom there was not the appearance of the fruits of faith and repentance, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1, 2, 3, 4. And ſeeing, by Mr. <hi>S.</hi> children were not baptized by <hi>John,</hi> and yet <hi>all Judea and Jeruſalem, and all the regions round about Jordane,</hi> came to <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.5. I hope he may be perſwaded that countrie and houſholds may be baptized, and yet children, ignorant, and profane, according to Chriſts command, may juſtly be debarred of the ſaid Goſpel-Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ch. 7. p. 49. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Elſe were your children unclean, but now are they holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118597:17"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All that are of Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s judgement, are ſo partial, and do ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently contradict themſelves in the application of holineſs, as pretending it relates unto childrens Baptiſm; in that, as they pretend to bring children into the Church, in that they ſay they are holy; ſo on the contrary, they excommunicate them out of the Church, from being partakers or members of the Body or Church in the Lords Supper, becauſe they want ſaith and holineſs, which is required in all communicants. Therefore I care the leſs to trouble my ſelf or others in further anſwering this wrangling conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: for they themſelves ſhew ſufficiently, that it is not relative holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as being appropriated to God, as the veſſels in the temple, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.5. but, it is the holineſs of converſation; which we nor they cannot ſee in a childe; the ground, with faith, of admiſſion into an Ordinance: which rule as they walk by in admiſſion unto the Supper; ſo, by the ſame rule they ought to walk, in the admiſſion into the Ordinance of Baptiſm. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. <hi>T.</hi> is not (as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſayth) too critical, to enquire whether children holy inherently, imputatively, or inviſibly: for unleſs there be a manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of holineſs, as the fruit of the inward grace, we ſee not a diſciple: and therefore man being judge of Baptiſm, cannot, by the rule or commiſſion of Chriſt, judge a childe to be baptized. And therefore as Fryer <hi>Toi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, That becauſe Angels were holy, we may pray, <hi>Hallowed be thy name:</hi> ſo Mr. <hi>S.</hi> pretending children are holy, <hi>ergo</hi> we may baptize them, is equally to be condemned.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> S. <hi>chap.</hi> 8 &amp; 9.</bibl> In which he endeavours, from the cutting off the Jews, and ingraffing in of the Gentiles, to relate to a viſible Church-memberſhip, in anſwering Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> eight Arguments to the contrary.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That, without any partiality, I cannot ſee but that Mr. <hi>T</hi>'s eight arguments are ſo unanſwered by Mr. <hi>S.</hi> that it were to eclipſe Mr. <hi>T</hi>'s light, and to take upon me an unneceſſary task, to anſwer Mr. <hi>S.</hi> Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi>'s eight Arguments ſhining more glorious, through the oppoſition made againſt them. That I may therefore onely hint ſomething that may further diſcover the myſtery of cutting off and graffing in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I conceive it cannot be underſtood of viſible Church-memberſhip, which is but a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and effect of Preaching; but hereby God hath declared, in a more general way, his total withdrawing away of his preſence, as denying the Jews, and affording of the Gentiles the means of ſalvation. So that we may underſtand <hi>root and branch,</hi> as root and ruſh or branch is explained, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.14. And therefore as <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 13.46. ſayth, <hi>It was neceſſary that the word of God ſhould firſt have been ſpoken unto you: but ſeeing you put it from you, and judge your ſelves unworthy of everlasting life, lo, we turn to the Gentiles;</hi> thus, there was a cutting off, and ingraffing in; rejecting the Jews, and affording of the Gentiles of the means of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>To proceed, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 10. pag. 88. ſheweth the harmony of <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. with <hi>Mark</hi> 10. and <hi>Luke</hi> 18. concerning the bringing of Infants to Chriſt, and his acts towards them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not to occaſion diſcord to ſuch a harmony, the ground of Mr.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118597:17"/>
               <hi>Philipus</hi> conſequence, which I though (thought many are not of that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) the ſtrongeſt conſequence that is pretended for Infant-baptiſm; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> &amp;c. may ſee, that we do deſire to declare, that we are ſo acted with the Spirit of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, to follow his ſteps, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. who is <hi>our forerunner, Heb.</hi> 9.20. in every thing; whereby the reign of Chriſt, in raiſing men up in the ſpirit of the Apoſtles and Prophets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. may be made viſible: that we may profeſs to imitate Chriſt, (Miracles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) in all things, in that Chriſt in all things: was the great ſervant of God in obeying, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.1. Therefore, I humbly conceive, they are not to be judged, that are made willing to imitate Chriſt, as in praying for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for meat and drink, and to bleſs the elements of bread and wine in the Lords Supper, if they alſo ſhall in imitation of Chriſt bleſs children, by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them: yet in this we have not the leaſt ground at all for the Goſpel-ordinance of baptiſm; though herein our <hi>Hannab</hi>-like love and care of children, to ſeek God for them, and that they may be brought up <hi>in the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and admonition of the Lord,</hi> is diſcovered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> S. chap. 11. pag. 103. wherein the method of God in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of a adminiſtring Ordinances in families, and baptizing houſholds, in the New Teſtament, how far it contributes to Infants baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though I acknowledge, as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hath declared, that <hi>Abraham</hi> and his houſe was circumciſed, and might alleadge that <hi>Abraham</hi> had no children in his houſe, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> being thirteen yeers old, and <hi>Iſaac</hi> as yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, when <hi>Abraham</hi> was circumciſed; yet this needeth not to be alleadged, for Mr. <hi>S.</hi> cannot prove that <hi>Abraham</hi> was brought into the Church, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church before: and <hi>Iſrael</hi> his ſon, if he were called to offer, or bring his offering unto the altar, was alſo a viſible member of the Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. And beſides, Circumciſion being but the ſigne of a temporal covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.8, 11. as I have before fully proved, therefore I ſee no ground, from <hi>Abraham</hi>'s houſhold being circumciſed, to be a preſident or method (as you call it) for bringing of children which cannot profeſs; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, upon profeſſion, Chriſt hath ordained all to be called to the Ordinance of Baptiſm. And that, which puts all out of doubt, the Scripture it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> clearly removes this ſcruple or ſuppoſition, in that when whole houſholds were baptized, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 10. <hi>Cornelius</hi> and all his houſe <hi>feared God:</hi> and of the Jayler and his houſhold that was baptized, it is ſaid, that <hi>he and all his houſe heard the word of God: Acts</hi> 16.32. was baptized, ver. 33. <hi>believing in God with all his houſe,</hi> verſ. 34. And when <hi>Paul</hi> baptized the houſhold of <hi>Stephanus,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16. it's ſaid in the ſame Epiſtle, chap. 16. verſ. 15. that the houſhold of <hi>Stephanus addicted themſelves to the miniſtery of the Saints:</hi> ſo that there is a conſtant method to the contrary. If there then had been a childe in <hi>Lydia</hi>'s houſe, ſhe going to hear, not knowing of Baptiſm (a thouſand families not having little children, as either not being married, barren, or ancient) I conceive the like would have been mentioned. And therefore I do not ſay, as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſaith, chap. 6. pag 47 that children were neglected: for if it had been the will of God, the Apoſtles would have readily baptized them, and would not have neglected their duty; nor would the holy Ghoſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118597:18"/>
ſo fully have declared the excluſion of children; or nominated, that all in the houſe believed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when houſholds were baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> S. chap. 12. pag. 109. in which Circumciſion and Baptiſm are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer: Mr. <hi>S.</hi> having pleaſed himſelf to roul over the ſame ſtone, (I may ſay, <hi>a ſtone of offence</hi>) in tumbling it back again, we being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled with it, chap. 1.2, 3. So that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> I ſuppoſe, will not finde it uſeful for his building: therefore I much admire, that he would compare Baptiſm and Circumciſion, and yet make them both look ſo like themſelves, as that, pag. 114. the one (he ſayth) cutting away ſin, as with a knife; and the other waſhing it away with water. In which words of Mr. S. there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth ſo much ſmoke in the temple, in this blinde Popiſh doctrine, as that I need not further confute it. And yet it is ſo precious in his eyes, as that the darkneſs of Uncharitableneſs hath ſo far poſſeſſed his ſpirit, (as I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſay) that he further hath judged his brethren, ſaying, That if they did with more ſobriety weigh ſuch conſiderations, they would not with ſuch fooliſh contempt write and ſpeak of Infant baptiſm.</p>
            <p>To which words of Mr. S. in ſoberneſs, plainneſs, and in the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, I ſay unto him, Brother, firſt take out the moat out of your own eyes, which makes you imagine you ſee your brethren want ſobriety and wiſdom, in that they cannot with you ſee that knife and water that cutteth off and waſheth away ſin. Who is moſt inconſiderate, I pray you? It is the blood of Chriſt, and not that of Circumciſion, which is the fountain; and not of water, that is ſet up for ſin and for uncleanneſs, <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch.</hi> 13.1. Did not Popery hold forth this doctrine, in teaching that Original ſin is waſhed away in Baptiſm? Certainly upon ſecond thoughts, I hope Mr. S. will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn his deſpiſed brethren of <hi>fooliſh contempt,</hi> it upon this account, as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery hath corrupted and perverted the Ordinance, they deny your doctrine concerning Baptiſm and Circumciſion, being thus by you made enemies to the croſs of Chriſt: and therefore there neither wants wiſdom nor ſobriety in thoſe, that upon this account do zealouſly oppoſe the aſcribing of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to Circumciſion and Infants baptiſm; ſeeing Circumciſion did never cut off ſin, and that Infant baptiſm is repugnant to the command of Chriſt in the Scripture. And though I am tyred, to meet again with Circumciſion, which was ſo ſilenced by the firſt General Aſſembly, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. as methinks it ſhould not be received by us that ſucced them;</p>
            <p>To anſwer further: That Circumciſion, as Mr. S. pretendeth, hath no correſpondency with Baptiſm, we may obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Baptiſm is upon profeſſion and prayer: but Circumciſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any prayer or profeſſion was inſtituted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Baptiſm hath relation to the Church called out of the world: but Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was onely the token of an entayl of inheritage, in which the world were gathered, or made a nation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Baptiſm brought in both men and women into the Church: but Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion had no relation to the female. And therefore I know not in what Baptiſm and Circumciſion may juſtly be compared.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118597:18"/>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 13. pag. 116. tells us, that <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. is a famous place holding forth correſpondencie betwixt Circumciſion and Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer. You ſee Circumciſion hath got upon the ſtage again, to plead its correſpondencie betwixt it and Baptiſm, from <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. from which you cannot expect any great <hi>applaudet,</hi> firſt, in that M. <hi>S.</hi> confeſſeth that ſome Divines are of contrary judgement. And if all be not, they may ſee cauſe of better information, if they conſider, that it is <hi>circumciſion made without hands</hi> which precedeth, verſ. 11. which Baptiſm cannot ſucceed, v. 12. And therefore this place which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> produceth, cannot be famous, except thereby, that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> produceth a place, whereby he is caſt with his own wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But I haſten.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 14. pag. 122.</bibl> 
               <hi>In which is a clear explication of</hi> Matth. 28.19. with Mark 16.15, 16. <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Arguments from the first inſtitution are opened and confuted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Arguments, and explanation of the commiſſion of Chriſt, <hi>Go and diſciple unto me, and baptize,</hi> is I hope ſo fully anſwered, that all the miſts, ſcruples, wrangling, and criticiſms, whereby Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to over-veil the commiſſion of Chriſt, are there ſo anſwered, that it will further appear, that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> is either under deluſion, or doth prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the command of Chriſt, in that he would have the expreſs and moſt plain words of Chriſt, <hi>Go teach and baptize,</hi> to mean ſprinkle an untaught diſciple: An implicite contradiction to the Goſpel-Ordinance, as in <hi>Mr.</hi> S. next chapter will more appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> S. <hi>chap.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. <hi>pag.</hi> 130. In which the ſignification, or what it is to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized, is diſcovered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That you may ſee what <hi>Mr.</hi> S. hath done in this buſineſs, and how little his Humane authority, which pag. 131. li. 1. he ſayth, are the beſt guides in this caſe: It cannot be denyed, but that after <hi>Mr.</hi> S produced <hi>Scapula, Paſor,</hi> and <hi>Grotius,</hi> to ſhew their judgement of Baptiſm, out of his ingenuity he confeſſeth (which is all which we deſire to be granted) that thoſe Authors, in the ſtricteſt ſenſe, acknowledge, and do interpret baptiſm for immerſion, that is, to be covered all over, or, as the Scripture ſaith, to be <hi>buried in baptiſm,</hi> Rom. 6.4. Now behold how Truth prevaileth! when <hi>Mr.</hi> S. ſet himſelf, and all his learning, to finde ſome ſcruple or doubt againſt the known received practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles in baptiſm, to try the teſt, and to ſee how it may be judged by man; his own witneſſes, <hi>Budeus, Scapula,</hi> and <hi>Grotius,</hi> confeſs, that in the ſtricteſt ſenſe, baptizing is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as we would have it. Yet notwithſtanding, <hi>Mr.</hi> S. doth with this Ordinance, as the Heathens (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us) did with Chriſt, in that they would not acknowledge him to be God, becauſe the Synod and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people had not ſeen him before his reſurrection. For, to deny the right uſe of water in baptiſm, <hi>Mr.</hi> S. flees to the Oracle of the Athenians. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wonderful! how gropes he, or ſtumbleth for light on the noon-day! or how hardly would he admit of Baptiſm? In that he ſaith the Athenians baptized pots or cups; what then? do you think them ſo ſlovenly, that they would onely ſprinkle their pots and cups, which are uſually put into, or waſhed all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118597:19"/>
over in the water? Alas, <hi>Mr.</hi> S. alas, this running under the fig-tree for ſhelter, diſcovers <hi>Eve</hi>'s nakedneſs. Truely, theſe critical fancies, and wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed allegations, will not hold water. You are deceived, if you think to blinde a ſeeing eye from beholding the right uſe of the element of water; into which Chriſt deſcended, was buried, and for this cauſe they choſe <hi>Jordano,</hi> for that there was much water there, to be the place for baptiſm. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though at the beginning of the Chapter, p. 130. and in the laſt lines but two, you have promiſed to clear up the miſt; yet indeed you have done nothing leſs. But it's no matter; the ſun of Truth can ſhine thorow your darkneſs, which cannot comprehend it. And that which makes me humbled, is this, that I ſee you do much endeavour to put a veyl upon the Word; ſo that p. 134. you ſay, <hi>Let us view</hi> (your veyl being caſt over) <hi>the Scriptures which they bring for maintaining of this ſignification, that is, to be covered over in baptiſm,</hi> Matth. 3.13. Act. 8.36, 37, 38. What think you, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> have not thoſe Scriptures ſatisfied you againſt ſprinkling, or pouring water on the face of a childe? Not to trouble you how much Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſtrives to evade with his diſtinction, <hi>ab &amp; ex,</hi> that Chriſt came not out of the water: as though <hi>Philip</hi> was not baptized as Chriſt, whom he confeſſeth to have come out of the water. Oh lamentable cavilling! what would he do? would he with his <hi>ab</hi> or <hi>ex</hi> deny the gonig into the water? or what would <hi>Mr.</hi> S. mean, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, p. 135. that <hi>Philip</hi> was as much in the water as the Eunuch? what, was <hi>Philip</hi> buried in the water as much as the eunuch? Lord make us truely humbled. How gladly would man uphold his ſandy foundation! or how loth is a lofty ſpirit to become humbled! Cannot a man baptize, or put ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man into the water, but he muſt go as much into the water as the party that he baptizeth? How Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſhould be able to anſwer to the third place, where it is ſaid, <hi>John was baptizing in Enon, neer Salim, becauſe there was much water there,</hi> in regard his ſprinkling ceremony ſpeaks his contradiction, I ſhall not ſpend time to no purpoſe, to anſwer more then I have ſaid, to what he can alleadge againſt the baptizing becauſe of much water; ſeeing that as Reaſon <hi>Janus</hi>-like hath two faces, ſome men have a face to object againſt any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> pag. 138.</bibl> 
               <hi>The last pretence commonly urged for this dipping, is from the analogie it hath with Christs burial:</hi> Rom. 6.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. Buried with him in baptiſm. <hi>Hence they ſay it is moſt clear, we must be dipt under water, elſe it will not repreſent a burial. In this they put all their confidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our confidence is in God and his Truth; and therefore we ſhall be ready to anſwer, if you can, more ſeriouſly then before, object any thing from Scripture to prove the contrary practice: And therefore let us hear what Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hath to ſay, pag. 138. in theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plunging the whole body in water, doth not repreſent burial: for the cuſtom of the Jews was, to cut out a place like a cave, or den, out of a rock, to lay their dead bodies: and, as it is obſerved by a man of great learning and diligence, Thus when we ſleep in our houſes we may be ſaid to be buried, having ſomething over our heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hath acknowledged, that to be covered over head,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118597:19"/>
repreſents burial; or to be buried in baptiſm, is to have the water covering us; in this he hath, whether he intended or no, juſtified our proceeding, and condemned his own ſprinkling buſineſs or ceremony. To what Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſayth further in this particular.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> pag. 139. relates,</bibl> 
               <hi>Secondly, the maner of burying in Europe, is not by plunging the body in a pit of dust, but by casting dirt or dung on the perſon: ſo that the pouring out water on the face of an infant, as a paſſive ſubject, ſeems more to anſwer the ſimilitude of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, then the caſting into the water, wherein there is ſome motion of the party himſelf, contributing to his baptiſm.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In that Chriſt went into the water, and prayed in the water; and that in imitation of Chriſt it is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 22.16. <hi>be baptized—calling upon the Name of the Lord;</hi> the myſtery of a burial is held forth, not ſo much from paſſive deadneſs, as in being ſeparated and covered in the water, whereby deadneſs in that act is declared. And this Mr. <hi>S.</hi> pag. 138. that to be cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is implyed in burial, and that this covering in water is not by ſprinkling: for in ſtead of covering the childe, to repreſent a burial, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> takes another courſe, or the Good-wives, by his permiſſion; for they take off the cloth, and make the childs face, that before was covered, to be uncovered, that he may ſprinkle a drop or two, or pour a little water on the face. Now hereby that he ſhould repreſent a burial, when he ſeems onely to rantize the face; it's known that the childe is ſo far from being covered, or hid from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or ſeparated, that the Goodwives hold it up in their arms, to be ranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the face of the Congregation. Which methinks Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſhould not fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to repreſent a burial: for in this he is as much miſtaken, as he is by the book, in that he tells us, pag. 141. that the Jaylor was baptized in priſon: for <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30. the Jaylor brought out <hi>Paul</hi> out of priſon, and after <hi>Paul</hi> had preached to the Jaylor, and to all his houſe, then the Jaylor was baptized: and that this was not in priſon, as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> dreamed, it is ſaid after he was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized: <hi>he brought them into his houſe,</hi> verſ. 34. But this miſtake is not ſo great, as that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hath thus far ſuffered his paſſion to be predominant, as to ſay, pag. 142. <hi>that if there be any abſolute need of dipping, it is to cool the heat of theſe mens ſpirits, who deny baptiſm to be true, becauſe they have not been plunged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Oh ſtrange! if this <hi>vox populi</hi> ſhould come from Chriſt, what's that he tells of cooling the heat of ſpirits? Alas, <hi>Phyſitian, cool your ſelf.</hi> But I hope he hath his check, as I am troubled for his levity: for that fire of zeal that is in the Saints, to own the due adminiſtration of the Ordinance in Baptiſm, is ſuch a fire of zeal, that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> is not able to quench it. And if there could be an outward remedy for hot ſpirits, it were a mercy that the ſparkles of Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s youthfulneſs were ſo far quenched, that it might not be his recreation to contradict the minde of Chriſt in the right uſe of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of water in baptiſm; which we do not, as Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſaith, aſcribe to plunging, but to be covered over, or buried with Chriſt in baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> chap. 16. pag. 148. endeavouring, that the waſhing of the body, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. was not meant by baptiſm; and his ſummoning up his former principles, as he calleth them, chap. 17. p. 154. and his buſineſs in troubling
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118597:20"/>
himſelf about the adminiſtration of baptiſm, chap. 18. being things that are not either granted, or denyed, prejudicial to the cauſe, no more neceſſary then his recapitulation of his former principles, which doth ſpend time, and make him tedious to the Reader, as what he hath alleadged in Chriſt's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing baptized by <hi>John,</hi> chap. 19. pag. 162. with his conceited Queſtion, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt did preach before he did baptize: All theſe Chapters being but <hi>ſtrife of words,</hi> and <hi>doubtful diſputations,</hi> I not ſtriving for maſtery, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as engaged, endeavouring to undeceive the deluded people, in holding forth the Truth; I ſeeing no edification for me to follow the flying ſhadows of needleſs conjectures, altogether as unedifying as <hi>endleſs genealogies:</hi> Therefore onely to the laſt Chapter, wherein Mr. <hi>S.</hi> holdeth forth, pag. 166. <hi>That Baptiſm doth not form a Church;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, That though Baptiſm doth no more form a Church, then it formeth a believer, no Church hath been found or acknowledged, which hath not been baptized. Therefore, though through the falling away from the Faith, Chriſtians can experience, that the work of grace, in giving a ſeal to the Miniſtery, and thereupon there hath been a yeelding up of one another to ſerve God with one conſent, whereby a Church hath been gathered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe members (as in the Churches of all Independents) they have been baptized: yet if the ſaid Independent Churches ſhould in mercy have their eys opened (as ſome can experience) to ſee and ſubmit to the minde of Chriſt in the Order of the Goſpel, whereby the firſt that is in baptiſm be laſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, then in this extraordinary work of grace, the work of grace upon full trial being approved of, that the ſaid Church be found to be gathered Saints, and the ſeal of the Miniſtery, then the ſaid Church, as a houſhold of faithful, without breaking their relation of Paſtor and Flock, they may be baptized. For we muſt not build upon another mans foundation; Chriſt himſelf own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the man that caſt out devils, though he followed not the Apoſtles: And though the Spouſes ſiſter want two breſts, yet was ſhe owned for their ſiſter, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.8. So that whatſoever work of God is wrought, it is to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged; provided that the Paſtor of the ſaid Church be baptized by ſuch a Paſtor of a Church that is under the practice of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Thus much in anſwer to Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s book, as it relates unto Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I ſhall onely make anſwer to that which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> firſt object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the doctrine of Baptiſm, and concerning the denying of ſinging of Pſalms, in his Epiſtle Dedicatory.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>S.</hi> Epiſt. Dedic.</bibl> 
               <hi>I have treated upon theſe two ſubjects, [viz. denying of Infant-baptiſm, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Pſalms] which eat mens affections, and creep at the heart like a gangrene, inſenſibly: An Opinion that hath been always ominous, and of a wonderful ſtrange influence, accompanied with the moſt dangerous retinue of Errours, ſince the firſt Embryo of it was brought forth; whether by the judgement of God, or from its natural and ſecret connexion with other principles of darkneſs, I will not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; onely God hath ſhewed ſome black characters upon it, in every nation where it hath prevailed: though we cannot but ſay, Many Saints are innocently under the power of it.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118597:20"/>To which, I return this anſwer:</p>
            <p>That Hypocrites drawn out of the element of the world, receiving the new wine of the doctrine of the kingdom of heaven, into the old bottles of their hearts, <hi>Hymenius</hi>-like, have made ſhipwrack of their profeſſion, makes not the Opinion always ominous: nor doth the abuſe of drink condemn the lawful enjoyment of the creature. For, if you had but taſted, you might have experienced, that the doctrine of baptizing of believers doth, like all other Truths, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.17. ſo ſanctifie, and work, through Chriſt, ſuch a ſpiritual union with Chriſt and all his Saints, that indeed a blinde and profane ſoul cannot live in the element of it. And therefore, if any ſuch appear, that have owned it, they either forſake the Church, or they are cut off by the Church, as withered branches: however, the evil complained of (if ever it be viſible) though a Gangrene, may be cured with the knife of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</p>
            <p>Yet on the contrary, ſuch inevitable evils attend Infant-Baptiſm, that it is the very heart-blood and pulſe of the ſoul of Antichriſt, and the onely partition-wall, which hinders the communion of Saints, and the greateſt let to the gathering and uniting of all Saints, into Truth and Church-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that can be: So that as long as it is in practice, the ſmoak ſhall not fully vaniſh out of the Temple. And therefore ſuch black characters do point it out, it being built upon the foundation of wreſted conſequences, implicite faith, blinde charity, and pretended antiquity, that Antichriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all the profane ſons of the world, plead their own birthright-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in it, and reſt under the cover or ſhelter of it: Though I muſt with Mr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> conclude, that many Saints do acknowledge it, and as owned by the world do decry it. And therefore it is to be hoped, that, as the Saints ſhall be more fully informed, Saint-like, they will renounce it, and will ſubmit, Chriſt like, unto the Ordinance of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing in controverſie, is the denying of ſinging of Pſalms; of which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſaith thus:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>I hope when mens Hearts come in tune, their Voices will likewiſe. The former denies more fundamental principles, as the Covenant in its extent and ſubjects, the freeneſs of grace, the riches of it working in the New Teſtament, and contracts the Goſpel, leaving more grace viſible in the Legal and Old Teſtament-diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then in the New.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As concerning Singing of Pſalms, Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, though I hope to make theſe to appear to be diſtinct, which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to be individually united; yet, as to the point in controverſie about Singing, this I have to ſay, That as Chriſt ſhall more and more raign, he ſhall rouze up and gather his Saints to be baptized into one body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14. and united into, and acted with the Spirit of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that their hearts will be in tune: That as Independent Churches caſt off In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-ſprinkling, ſo Churches of Chriſt under baptiſm will return (as ſome of them for the preſent are) unto ſinging. And yet I finde, that thoſe that are not under the preſent practice, dare not deny their title to the Ordinance of Singing. But that denying Infant-baptiſm is worſe, or that there is any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118597:21"/>
evil at all, but a ſubmiſſion to the Ordinance and Commiſſion of Chriſt, in denying of Infant baptiſm; I muſt needs therefore further ſay, That to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend baptiſm of Infants to be helpful to exalt free grace, is abſolutely to deny the grace of God to be free, which is conveyed without the Ordinance of baptiſm. And that the childe of a reprobate may be as ſoon under the Covenant of Free-grace, as the childe of a believer: And that no man can judge who are under the Covenant of Free grace, and who are not. And therefore we do not baptize upon this account, but as we ſee grace, faith, and conſent viſibly appearing. And therefore their pretended light, that will baptize the children of believers onely, as from free grace pretended, is moſt full of darkneſs. And if free grace had been a ground of baptiſm, man could not have been the judge. And that God doth require man to do nothing ignorantly, or doubting: and therefore hath expreſly commanded (though hypocrites may falſly pretend to ſubmit unto the Rule; and in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them upon that account, man is no offender) who we ſhall baptize, even every one that is diſcipled by teaching. And therefore we leaving to act upon the pretence of the Covenant of Free-grace, we do not deny chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren any outward warrantable priviledge, that was granted them before <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s days, in his days, or ever was done by Chriſt or his Apoſtles, in preſenting them to God, in praying for a bleſſing for them, and to bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord; that as ſoon as ever this ſecret will of God, in his free grace, ſhall be revealed, They may, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the command and example of Chriſt and all his Churches, paſs the Goſpel-Ordinance of Baptiſm.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118597:21"/>
            <head>QUESTIONS and ANSWERS concerning the baptizing of Believers onely, the manner of the adminiſtration of the Ordinance, with the reaſons that may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Magiſtrate to encourage the preaching thereof in Publike.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion</hi> 1. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether is Baptiſm a Goſpel-Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> In that<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</note> Chriſt himſelf is the author of it, and did after his<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.7, 16.</note> reſurrection from the dead immediately command it, and that all the Saints upon their profeſſion of ſaith were accordingly baptized: Therefore Baptiſm doth appear to be a Goſpel-Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>Whether may baptiſm be called a Seal?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In that man is judge of baptiſm, and that it is againſt the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and truth of God to ſeal to a blank, or<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4, 5.</note> uncertain condition; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore baptiſm is no Seal, though commonly ſo called.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>What do you call Baptiſm, if it be not a Seal?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Baptiſm is a<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2.</note> principle of the foundation of the doctrine of Chriſt, a Goſpel-Ordinance, the<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>anſwer of a good conſcience</hi> towards God and man, and a<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</note> figure of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>What is the end for which baptiſm was ordained?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In that Chriſt commanded to<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15.</note> preach the Goſpel to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and yet onely to baptize ſuch as are<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</note> diſcipled, or are taught the word of God, or believed; it doth therefore clearly appear, that God in Chriſt did ordain Baptiſm, to this end, that Chriſt might<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16.</note> ſeparate the election of grace, by<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</note> calling them out of the world, into the<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 9.19, 27.</note> fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Church, and to unite all ſo called, in the profeſſion of ſaith, in their baptiſm, and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 9.39.</note> breaking of bread, in which they communicate.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>How can you prove, that by theſe words of Chriſt,</hi> Go and preach the Goſpel to every creature, Go and make diſciples, and baptize them, He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved, <hi>is ſo to be interpreted,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with 46, 47.</note> 
               <hi>that none but thoſe that believe are to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the Apoſtles and Church of Chriſt did thus underſtand them, as by their doctrine and practice doth appear.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118597:22"/>Queſt. 6. <hi>Where have the Apoſtles taught, that none but thoſe that hear and believe, ſhould be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In that the Apoſtles have taught, that thoſe that are baptized, ought to<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.</note> repent, be<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. Rev. 18.4.</note> called out of the world, have the<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</note> anſwer of a good conſcience towards God and man; and have declared that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.37.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs hinders baptiſm: therefore by their doctrine it doth appear, that none but ſuch as hear and believe, ſhould be baptized.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>And did the Apoſtles onely baptize believers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes verily, they onely baptized viſible profeſſors; as, when they<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12.</note> believed <hi>Philip,</hi> preaching the things concerning the kingdom of God, and the Lord Jeſus, they were baptized, both men and women: and when<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10 2, 44, 48.</note> houſholds were baptized, the Scripture doth declare, that they all<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10 2, 44, 48.</note> feared God, received the<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10 2, 44, 48.</note> holy Ghoſt,<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16 with chap. 16.15.</note> gave themſelves to the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Word of God,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26 32, 34.</note> heard the word of God,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26 32, 34.</note> rejoyced in God, and<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26 32, 34.</note> believed.</p>
            <p>Qu. 8. <hi>If this be ſo, then neither children nor unbelievers ought be baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's true indeed: for as in Circumciſion, when the male was one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly named, the female was excluded; ſo when Chriſt onely ordained that thoſe that hear and believe ſhould be baptized, unbelievers, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, muſt needs be excluded.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>How comes it then to paſs, that this doctrine of baptiſm hath not been before revealed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though the doctrine of baptiſm hath been always profeſſed, yet it hath not been generally received, for theſe reaſons. 1. Becauſe there was<note n="‖" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3.</note> a falling away from the faith, whereby all the Ordinances of Chriſt were perverted and corrupted, by the<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.8.</note> ſmoak which was to continue till the Lamb's ſouldiers ſhould procure the free courſe of the Goſpel. 2. The tayl of the beaſt is to ſtrike down the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.4.</note> third part of the ſtars, even lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (not under the powerful means of information) which ſhall walk under the ſparkles of their own Conſequences. 3. Becauſe that though Antichriſt, before theſe times, hath been revealed, as oppoſing the perſon and merits of Chriſt, yet the Ordinances are but beginning to be cleared; in diſcovery whereof, the Church begins to be reſtored to the purity of the primitive time of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. 4. In ſuch a caſe as this, where things are admitted, as Infant-baptiſm, being the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion men were brought up in (though godly) yet it is not queſtioned, till men be put upon it, or otherwiſe by God extraordinarily called: for which cauſe, Infant-baptiſm hath not been much queſtioned.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 10. <hi>What will become of all the world, the unbelievers and children, if they be not baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt muſt be preached to all the<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6</note> world, to every Pariſh, even to capable children, and unbelievers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as they ſhall have an ear to hear, and be<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4</note> called out of Babylon, they ought to be baptized, and receive the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42.</note> Lords ſupper, with the gathered Churches of believers.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 11. <hi>How ſhall we be able to judge believers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16.</note> fruits of their profeſſion, or holy converſation; and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118597:22"/>
in that they are willing to be united unto, and<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14.</note> love the Saints, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41.</note> government of Chriſt under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>But may not unbelievers, like Simon Magus, come to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes. a garden may have weeds, and<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.</note> tares may be ſown with the good ſeed; yet, as the Church is to<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2, 3, 4.</note> judge of her members, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them into communion; ſo hath the Church power to exclude them alſo out of her communion.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the way of the adminiſtration of baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Chriſtian diſciple that is to be baptized, muſt,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.15.</note> Chriſt-like, upon the profeſſion of faith and obedience, deſcend to be<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</note> covered or buried in water,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 12.16 comp. with <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.21.</note> calling upon the Name of the Lord, being baptized in the Name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt: which being done, thoſe Chriſtians which are baptized, are (as brethren) to be received by the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9 26</note> Church, by the<note n="‖" place="margin">Gal. 3.9.</note> right hand of fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 14. <hi>But may not ſprinkling of water ſuffice in baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No: there can be no baptiſm in ſprinkling or partial dipping: for in ſprinkling, the right uſe of water is as much perverted, as when<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.15.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> ſpared part of the ſheep, though he intended them for Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And beſides, in the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</note> burying of the whole body in water, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of being buried with Chriſt unto his death; and the raiſing out of the water, to be conformable to the reſurrection of Chriſt, is not onely revealed, but in the baptized, humbling of themſelves, proſtrated <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> like before God in the loweſt element, there is a ſubmiſſion to the acknowledgement of the profeſſion of Chriſt in the Goſpel; which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done or demonſtrated in ſprinkling, which neither ſenſe, reaſon, Scripture, nor any Author, profane or divine, can judge to be baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 15. <hi>Whether is it not then a ſin to baptize Infants?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That we may judge no man but by viſible appearance, it's without controverſie, that they which baptize the children of all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or other mens Pariſhes without exception, ſin againſt the light of their own pretended conſequences.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 16. <hi>But may not God accept of the good meaning and intention of man, though the rule or command be not altogether obſerved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the ſprinkling of an Infant, there is nothing at all, either in the taught diſciple, that ought to be baptized, or of the uſe of water in baptiſm. And therefore intend or imagine what we pleaſe, the Ordinance is ſo totally perverted, that after information, I do not know how the Lord can be ſaid to<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30.</note> wink at ſuch ignorance.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 17. <hi>Whether is the childe damned, if it die unbaptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not in man to judge, that any childe that dieth is either ſaved or damned:<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29.</note> ſecret things belong unto God, and if in Gods election it be ſaved, want of baptiſm cannot hinder, nor the pretended enjoyment thereof alter the decree of Gods Predeſtination.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 18. <hi>But may not conſequences be admitted, to prove Infants ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In ſuch a caſe as this of Baptiſm, where there is (as Queſt. 5,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118597:23"/>
6, 7. hath been proved) an expreſs command and example to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Conſequences cannot be admitted of, leſt we ſhould<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20</note> reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and reſiſt his commandment.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 19. <hi>Wherein do we reſiſt or reaſon againſt the command of Chriſt in Infant-ſprinkling?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In baptizing of an Infant, when we are commanded to baptize a taught diſciple, 1. We bring the wiſdom of Chriſt in queſtion, as though he ſhould forget to except againſt a childe by name, having in the taught diſciple already excepted againſt both the ignorant and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants; as in wiſdom God, in onely commanding the male to be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, the female, though not otherwiſe excepted againſt, was expreſly excluded.</p>
            <p>Again, when Chriſt ſaith, Baptize a taught diſciple; for us by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to interpret this command to belong to ſucking children, is to make Chriſt guilty of an implicite contradiction, or to deny, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, gainſay, or confute himſelf, as to ſay, A wiſe fool: Therefore no Conſequences, whereby we would uphold Infant-ſprinkling, ought, in contradiction to Chriſts command, be at all pretended; but as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in this Ordinance of baptiſm, we muſt have the faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> or believe according to the example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſubmit to Chriſts expreſs<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.15.</note> command, as hath been declared, without any reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 20. <hi>Why do men then uſually, for the most part, rage againſt the baptizing of believers onely, ſeeing it is according to the expreſs command and example of Christ and his Apoſtles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the election of grace (before, through powerful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, they have the means of ſeeing) oppoſe the Truth of which they are ignorant. 2. The world, which is the multitude of unbelievers, neither will nor can acknowledge to receive any<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.</note> truth which doth ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie, but as it is commanded by Law, or acknowledged by cuſtom. 3. The baptiſm of believers onely, is ſuch a ſtrict way or profeſſion of godlineſs, that the generality do rage againſt it, ſo that the Papiſts and moſt licentious cannot endure to profeſs it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 21. <hi>But may not the Magiſtrate ſtint or limit the publike Preachers to obſerve an Uniformity, and ſuppreſs this doctrine of Baptiſm, as being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the tradition and preſent practice of the Church of</hi> England?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All formerly-received Doctrinal Truths and Traditions of the Churches, ought not as a Foundation (which is Chriſt in his Word) be ſo peremptorily and forcibly enjoyned, as that the authority and truth thereof may not be queſtioned, or, upon a true and full diſcovery thereof, be altered or reformed; ſeeing, to limit and force publike Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, ſo that none may buy or ſell without that mark, was and is the deſigne of Antichriſt, whereby he tyrannized over the Saints, and their moſt glorious lights were put under a buſhel: Therefore all private and publike Preachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are to be<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.14.</note> limited onely to the Word of God, and not otherwiſe. And therefore, if the Lord ſhall be pleaſed to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118597:23"/>
reveal himſelf to any publike Teacher, more and more to pull off the veil from off the Word, and to bleſs his endeavours in calling the Election of grace out of <hi>Babylon;</hi> this work of grace, as it ſhall appear in any Pariſh, is to be owned and encouraged: provided, that the Word be not ſo wreſted, or pretended to be interpreted, as may deny the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Truth, which Chriſt after his reſurrection did immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to be preached to all Nations, that is to ſay, to teach and baptize them, in the Name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, and to obſerve all things whatſoever he hath commanded, with belief of his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.19, 20.</note> preſence to this way, and faithfulneſs to make good all other his promiſes, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance and priviledges of all faithful Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 22. <hi>But may it ſtand with the honour of the Magiſtrate, to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the profeſſors of this doctrine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In that, for divers yeers, we have experienced, that the Lord is<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.26.</note> fulfilling of his prophecie, to ſend Magiſtrates to take away the droſs and tin, and to reſtore the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25</note> dominion of the Saints, in the enjoyment of their Laws and Languages, which were taken from them by the fourth Beaſt, or laſt Monarchy:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1, 14.</note> and that they are the Lamb's ſouldiers that ſhall pour out the ſeventh Vial; that as former Monarchs brought in ſmoak or darkneſs into the Temple, ſo Goſpel-Magiſtrates, by their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of publike ſhining lights, ſhall be glorious inſtruments to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore again the light into the Temple, or publike Meeting-place for Gods Worſhip. And in that the Magiſtrates have alſo, according to their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo far oppoſed viſibly appearing<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.</note> unſound doctrine, having put their hand to Gods Plough, in cutting down the Epiſcopal tree, and in abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing the Service book; it muſt needs be then their honour, crown, and glory, ſo to finiſh the good work begun, ſo that Parochial ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the root of the Epiſcopal tree, having its life and moiſture in the old Service-book, which is aboliſhed, may not in this great light of the Goſpel be replanted, or ſo ſuffered to take root again, ſo as to ſhoot out more wilde olive-branches, or ſons of oppoſition, under which the moſt ignorant and Popiſh party are ſtill nouriſhed; or ſo to favour it, as not to ſuffer the Goſpel-Ordinance to grow beſide it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 23. <hi>But is it conſisting with the peace of this Nation, (ſo many oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and being diſaffected to this doctrine) for the Magiſtrate to tolerate it in publike?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As no Ordinances (the fruits of faith) are to be forced; ſo there is little appearance of God in them, or they are not at all conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, that being not forced to this doctrine, become the troubled ſea, to be offended with ſuch Saints that receive this Goſpel-Truth that is preached unto them, and that the peace by any ſuch ſhall be diſturbed or broken; the Lord, which hath ſo promiſed his preſence, &amp; hath ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theſe and other Saints in procuring the peace of this Nation, that the Saints of Gathered Churches are ready to ſacrifice their lives to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118597:24"/>
maintain the peace of the Nation, under the preſent Government. And therefore the Magiſtrate may expect, in the promiſed preſence of Chriſt to this Way really ſubmitted unto, the bleſſing of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves, and the eſtabliſhing of the Peace and Righteouſneſs of the Nation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118597:24"/>
            <head>A Declaration to the Election of Grace, who, for want of information, are either igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of, or enemies unto the Goſpel-Ordinance of Baptizing of BELIEVERS onely.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly beloved in the Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the falling away from the faith (which was foretold by the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note> Apoſtle) was fulfilled, the man of ſin as it is ſaid, or popiſh Antichriſt, did not onely ſit in the temple of God oppoſing himſelf above all that is called God or is worſhipped; but as fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told he brought the ſmoak of ignorance &amp; ſtrong deluſions into the Temple: and though he pretends infallibility, yet Satan like, that abode not in the truth, he cannot receiv the love of the truth. And therfore the Maſter-peice, or great deſign of the man of ſin, was and yet is to endeavor by lying wonders &amp; all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs, to corrupt all the Ordinances or commands of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.<note place="margin">The Pope or Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt did corrupt all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but eſpecially Baptiſm.</note> And therefore though Antichriſt had a great deſigne againſt faſting, which he hath perverted and corrupted in reſpect of ſet daies, and ordering a white meal, or to eat and drink when they faſt; as prayer by him is alſo corrupted and perverted in the Popiſh uſe of ungodly forms, pictures, and invocation of Saints and Angels ſinging with an unknown voice; as he hath alſo made the Lords day of no effect by ſporting and playing, and the obſervation of holy daies: and though he hath blaſphemed the doctrine, and deprived the people of the cup of the Lord, in the Ordinance of the Lords Supper, and hath totally perverted the gathering and government of the Churches of Chriſt, as far as his perſecuting power extendeth; yet in all theſe he hath no ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious deſigne, as in the perverting of the Goſpel-Ordinance of baptizing of believers onely. And yet behold the power of God, how by weak and contemptible means the Son of God is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that he might deſtroy the works of the Devil, in that, though Infants ſprinkling paſt the muſter of a notable outward reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118597:25"/>
and was almoſt endenized into the profeſſion of ſome Saints, and that great Champions threw down the Gantlet of Arguments, to fight with the Weapons of conſequences &amp; traditions to defend the ſame; yet behold, the Lord makes the flock, or common people, to ſee the truth when almoſt all publick teachers were overvailed, and could not burſt thorow the cloud of deluſion: until at laſt the Lord ſaw his time to trouble &amp; thereby make the diſcovery of his light unto the publick Miniſtry by calling ſome of them to trim up their lamps, that they may ſhine in the diſcovery of the mind of Chriſt in baptizing of beleivers onely. Do not then queſtion, why not before now you are called to witneſs your profeſſion: the Kingdom of Heaven is not got by obſervation. What are we, that we ſhould withſtand God, or hate to be reformed? Ariſe, why ſleep ye? the light ſhineth, the Bridegroom calleth: ſearch the Scriptures, and try whether it be of God or no. Do not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look Chriſt in the Manger: the Star ſhines, let us with the wiſe men worſhip and preſent our ſelves unto him, unto whom it doth direct us. What is the <hi>Egypt.</hi> Reed of humane Tradition, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate reſolution, that you ſhould rely upon? or do you fear to be put out of the Synagogue? Is not the Rigteous as bold as a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Great indeed is <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> great is the power of the Prince of darkneſs: but greater is the truth of God, and his light, which is able to diſpel the darkneſs both of Pope and people. Did not the truth alwaies when it was revealed, and think you it ſhall not now as well as ever (if God intend mercy to <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.) marvailouſly prevail? Did not the Doctrine of Baptiſm cauſe the Phariſees and people, yea the whole election of grace, to follow <hi>John</hi> into the Wilderneſs? And did not thoſe that were bewitched with <hi>Simons</hi> Sorceries, when they beleived <hi>Philip</hi> concerning the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Lord Jeſus, become baptized, both men and women? Shall not then, if Chriſt be fully preached indeed, overturn, overturn your parochiall legal, worldly union, and gather the election of grace out of every pariſh, to be members of the church of Chriſt your Saviour? You know, or may come to experience the truth thereof, that his people ſhall be willing in the day of his power: his ſheep ſhall hear his voice; but that ſtrange voice of baptizing Infants, never ſpoken of in the Scripture, ſhall they not hear. Come, let us reaſon the caſe: can
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118597:25"/>
Pedobaptiſm be a plant that our Heavenly Father hath planted, that ſpreads forth its luxurious branches, and makes a ſhadow for the world to reſt themſelves under, in the Cradle of ſecurity?<note place="margin">Baptized diſciples falſly ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</note> Cloſe not your eyes, nor ſhut your ears againſt the revelation of truth, though common fame would afright you, as ſome did the Iſraelites, to obſtruct their marching into <hi>Canaan,</hi> telling them, that there were great Zamzummims there: and therefore if you will believe them, they will tell you what monſtrous people the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts are: if you look that way, you ſhall loſe your ſelves in the midſt of darkneſs and deluſions; they will draw you away from all Scriptures and Ordinances: but try before you truſt, and ſearch into their profeſſion, and you ſhall ſee the contrary, that there was ever any way of God, but it was ever evill ſpoken of. Did they not ſay of <hi>John</hi> the baptiſt, that he had a Devil?<note place="margin">The way of God ever evil ſpoken of.</note> Did not the world caſt ſpots of reproaches in our Maſters face, who was without ſinne, or any ſpot or wrinkle? If they do theſe things to the green Tree, what will they do to the dry? Were not the old profeſſors, ſhortly after the times of the Apoſtles, in that they called one another Brother and Siſter, accuſed of inceſt and forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation? and when they were forced to forſake the world and went into caves, did not the <hi>Troubled Sea,</hi> the Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> caſt mire and dirt into their faces, ſaying, That they laid lurking there to rob and ſpoil thoſe that paſſed by?<note place="margin">Juſt. Mart. <hi>Apol.</hi>
               </note> ſo that <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> was forced to make an Apology for their juſtification. And thus <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Martin Bucer,</hi> &amp;c. were ſlandered with them by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches: and yet they were no more troubled,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex</hi> Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrard.</note> then <hi>Luther</hi> was with the Popes Bull, of which he ſaid, <hi>O Bulla vere Bulla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum filia!</hi> Be not then diſcouraged, you know this is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their condemnation, but of your ſalvation. Its enough to give an account of faith, and that in the name of God, to aſſure you, that there is nothing to be owned but Chriſt and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; whereby he is our Saviour, and hath made himſelf an example for us to imitate him in all things, (Miracles excepted.) But alas all the pretences and conſequences that the moſt learned can produce cannot make the deluſion of ſprinkling children to be baptiſm: God that never lyed, did never require an action to be done againſt ſence and reaſon; nor can repreſentations or intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alter an expreſs command to the contrary. Were it enough,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118597:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118597:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118597:27"/>
think you if any of you bid ſhould your ſervant give a cup of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a thriſty ſoul; were it enough for that ſervant to put his hand into the cup, and ſprinkle the man in the face with two or three drops of water? were this to obey his Maſters command? I trow not: and yet no more is done in ſprinkling of children, in anſwering the Comand of Chriſt in Baptiſm. And though this might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and that you might ſay with the Eunuch, Lo here is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, what letteth that the Child may not be baptized? To this, the ſame anſwer muſt be returned, that <hi>Philip</hi> made to the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch. If the Child can beleive with all its heart, it may: but let the Child alone, though it may be pretended to be the Child of a believer, We know, or may know, that believers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,<note place="margin">Rebaptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Acts 19.1, 2, 3, 4</hi> In the caſe of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal truth, or of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for Baptiſm.</note> which were really and fully baptized, becauſe they were at that time ignorant of the holy Ghoſt were upon that account (all the fundamentals being not revealed without which baptiſm can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be warrantable) rebaptized: when we were ſprinkled, great darkneſs, in compariſon of the light of Goſpel-reformation that now ſhineth, was then as a cloud over-veiling the Word. What hole can cavill find to ſeek evaſion, unleſs we ſay we are not believers? Is it not then the duty of Diſciples to imitate their Lord and Maſter, who in ſubmitting to this glorious Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance made himſelf our example, in which he was ſaid to fulfill all righteouſneſs? This is the way to humble a ſoul to give ſatisfaction of the profeſſion of Faith, and the teſtimony of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; to this the preſence of Chriſt, our peace light, and life, and protection is promiſed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tindal</hi>'s wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Mommon, fol. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> That you intend no evill, is eaſily to be believed: But as <hi>Tindall</hi> the bleſſed Martyr ſaid, That though <hi>Peter</hi> of a good minde or intention would perſwade Chriſt not to have ſuffered yet Chriſt for all that called him Satan. Its one thing to have a good intention, and another to do of knowledge. God (ſaith he) hath made a teſtament between him and us, wherein is contained both what he would have us to do and what he would have us to ask of him: ſee therefore thou do nothing to pleaſe God withall, but what he commandeth. And that they might be good and Godly men, and Martyrs, that were never more then ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ten Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in</hi> Eng. Hen. 8. <hi>anno</hi> 1553.</note> it may be granted; but then it was the time that the ſmoak was in the Temple. Martyrs have ſuffered for the profeſſion of the baptizing of believers only, but never any Martyrs have ſuffered
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118597:27"/>
in the defence of Infant pretended baptiſm. If we would look on humane example, It not for us to ſay as thoſe obſtinate unbelievers that the Maryr <hi>Stephen</hi> reproved, who ſaid, <hi>As our Fathers did, ſo will we do.</hi> Can there be any more precious in our eyes then to be led by the example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles? If you be not of the election of grace, if you would you ought not to be baptized. And if God have elected us, and we live under the means, our hearts and judgements ſhall be changed, we ſhall be the people that ſhall be made willing in the day of Chriſts power, whether you will or no. Ceaſe then, poor ſouls, be humble and patient, and wait till you ſee that God will do with you: ſhoot not your bolt to wound your Saviour, through the ſides of his deſpiſed Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: Be ye the Diſciples of Doctor <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> untill Chriſt make you his. It was the Phariſees and Lawyers that rejected the counſell of God againſt themſelves, and would not be baptized, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.30. but the election of grace muſt needs ſubmit. As they are under the means of information, they have a promiſe to be effectually called: they cannot cloſe their eyes,<note place="margin">All the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of grace, as they ſhall be under the means, ſhall profeſs Baptiſm.</note> as the means of ſeeing is revealed unto them: and if they have light already, and yet ſee not in ſomething that is newly diſcovered, then they are like a man in a dark Dungeon that ſeeth as ſoon as the window or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Scripture is opened unto them. But no light, no means can make a blind man ſee, whom God will not call, though the heavenly Lamp were never ſo reſplendent: And though a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man ſhine as a Star in the Church, yet ſhall the taile of the Beaſt caſt him down from the new Heaven or the Church, into his proper place or earthly Element: he cannot finiſh his courſe, he cannot (like his tempter) abide in the truth; he cannot receive the love of the truth that he might be ſaved. But on the contrary,<note place="margin">Joh. 4.44. 2 Theſſ. 2.10.</note> all the election of grace, they cannot (though with <hi>Paul</hi> they have commiſſion to perſecute the Saints, nay though they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the truth as divers<note n="*" place="margin">Archbiſh. <hi>C.</hi> Io. Baya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer.</hi>
               </note> Martyrs did) reſt till at length they return to their firſt love, and to the profeſſion of the Goſpel from whence they are fallen. Let us then content our ſelves (if our Maſter be pleaſed to call but a few to ſerve him) if we be in the number of that few that are called. Let the election then wait on the means, and ſee what God will do or diſpoſe of them, and not trouble themſelves like <hi>Zobedee's</hi> Mother, to deſire that for her Children, that cannot be granted her.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118597:28"/>To conclude therefore, either to ſtop the mouths of oppoſers, or to open the heart, (as the Lord is pleaſed) if at this time you will hear his voice, that hath commanded to baptize believers; if reaſon may be heard, or true information may not be deſpiſed, you may ſee in the confeſſion or practices of contrary judgements, as much as may raze down the foundation of Infant pretended bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Artic.</hi> 27. Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> in that it is acknowledged, that there is no expreſs tearms in the Scripture for Pedobaptiſm; and that by experience it may be ſufficiently evidenced in our hearts and conſciences, as is made viſible, that ſuch inevitable evils follow Infants ſprinkling, as that it brings all the World into the Church, which ſhould be called out of the World, and is the onely obſtacle or cauſe of the diviſion of all gathered Churches, they differing nothing, but in Infant ſprinkling, in which the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or rather the World forced into order, is in preſent practiſe; and from which, all the Churches of Chriſt ought to be totally ſeparated, or effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called out of <hi>Babylon:</hi> the very conſequences by which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants-ſprinkling, a meer deluſion and prevarication to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, as mens inventions, being altogether groundleſs and unwarrantable, and though proved, are of no force or validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to contradict the expreſs command or example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Let then all real, zealous, ſincere, converted Chriſtians hear Chriſts voice, who hath commanded to teach and baptize all Nations; and let them with all their old fellow-ſervants, deſire to imitate Chriſt their Maſter, who was baptized to make himſelf an example to fulfill all righteouſneſs. And let us not think that his arm is ſhortened, that he cannot help; or that he is not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, who in this Goſpel-Ordinance hath promiſed his preſence, in which all the Saints have found, and ever unto the end of the World ſhall moſt ſurely find their onely protection, comfort, peace, and glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
